<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Five sermons preached upon severall occasions (The texts whereof are set downe in the next page.) By Iohn Seller.</title>
            <author>Seller, John, 1592 or 3-1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 138 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11881</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101223</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837040</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837040</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1344</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11881)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1344)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 975:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Five sermons preached upon severall occasions (The texts whereof are set downe in the next page.) By Iohn Seller.</title>
                  <author>Seller, John, 1592 or 3-1648.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 270 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by B. Alsop and T. Fawcet] for Iohn Clark, and are to be sold at his shop under St. Peters church in Cornehill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Errata on verso of M6, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>First leaf blank except for signature mark.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Chicago. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1344:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1344:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FIVE SERMONS PREACHED upon ſeverall Occaſions. (The Texts whereof are ſet downe in the next Page.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> IOHN SELLER.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug. de Doct. Chriſt. lib. 1. cap. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Omnis res quae dando non deficit, dum habetur, &amp; non datur, non dum habetur.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for IOHN CLARK, and are to be ſold at his Shop un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Cornehill.</hi> 1636.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:1344:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1344:2"/>
            <head>The Texts of the ſeverall Sermons.</head>
            <list>
               <label>Serm. I.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>PSAL. 116.16.</hi> O Lord tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I am thy ſervant, I am thy ſervant. <hi>Preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King at</hi> Bagſhow, <hi>upon Tueſday,</hi> Septemb. <hi>15. 1635.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Serm. II.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>IOHN, 21.22.</hi> If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee? Follow thou mee. <hi>Before the King at</hi> Hampton <hi>Court, upon Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> Septemb. <hi>27. 1635.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Serm. III.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>IOHN, 1.16.</hi> And Grace for grace. <hi>To the Houſhold at</hi> White-Hall, <hi>Novemb. 29. 1629.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1344:3"/>
                  <hi>IV.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>
                  <hi>ECCLES. 12.1.</hi> Remember now thy Creator in the dayes of thy Youth.</item>
               <label>V.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>IOHN, 20.17.</hi> Touch me not, for I am not yet aſcended to my Father.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>in<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> has Conciones â Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino <hi>Iohanni Sellero</hi> habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, perlegi, nec in iis quicquam reperio quò minùs Cum utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate publicâ imprimantur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>SA: BAKER.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ex aedibus Londin:</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Martii die ultimo 1636.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1344:3"/>
            <head>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Serm. </seg>I</label> THE FIRST SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 116.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>O Lord truely I am thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, I am thy ſervant.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He feare of the Lord is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and <hi>the end of all things is this, Feare GOD and keepe his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Nay, the meanes which happily joyneth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether this beginning and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1344:4"/> this end, is ſtill the ſame; <hi>Bleſſed is the man that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes feareth.</hi> This is the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, the progreſſe, the cloſe of all true practicall Religion: and this happy beginning, and this happy end is the ſubject which I ſhall now commend unto you from the example of the Prophet in my text, <hi>O Lord, truly I am thy ſervant, I am thy ſervant.</hi> In the handling of which words, three pious obſervations there are which I ſhall now preſent unto you. The firſt is this.</p>
            <p>Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is our Lord and Maſter, and we muſt doe him ſervice; <hi>O Lord I am thy ſervant:</hi> an argument
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1344:4"/> wherin I ſhall not ſo much need proofes as perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Whom have I in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven but thee, and whom on earth in compariſon of thee?</hi> He that knoweth there is a God, cannot but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, the onely difficultie is to winne our hearts to proportion our ſervice to his love; <hi>Thou art my God and I will thanke thee, thou art my God and I will praiſe thee.</hi> We all know there was a time, if I may ſo ſpeake, before all time, a time of Eternitie before all time of ſucceſſion, when GOD by himſelfe inioyed all fulneſſe of complacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in himſelf. For, as the Sunne in the Heavens ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in its full brightneſſe,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1344:5"/> though there were no earth to ſhine upon; ſo the brightneſſe of Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was then it its full lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre, when Trinity in Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and Vnitie in Trinity, as it is now all things to all, was then all things to it ſelfe: Angels and men, and for their ſakes Heaven and earth, when in the powerfull and gracious counſell of his will with a word ſpeaking onely, he created: all this was done, not that thereby he might augment his glory, but communicate it. For, <hi>can a man be profitable unto God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob, 22.</note> and yet who is there to whom God hath not beene profitable? He ſtands not in need of our ſervice, but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1344:5"/> we cannot live without his command. When one man waites upon another, there is for the moſt part a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall dependance on each other: the ſervant cannot live without his Maſter, the Maſter knowes not how to want his ſervant. The glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of a King is upheld by the multitude of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: for let Subjects with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw their alleagiance, and we ſee Princes themſelves are but private men, and therefore we reade in the ſtate of <hi>Rome,</hi> that when the commons, upon termes of diſcontent, withdrew themſelves from the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, the Nobles were forc't to become petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners unto the commons,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1344:6"/> and to remit ſomewhat of the rigour of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that they might hold them afterward more conſtant in their ſervice. But looke upon our great Maſter, the King of Kings, and wee ſhall finde no ſuch depending references: Let all the world withdraw themſelves from him, yet ſtill <hi>[Deus ſolus is Deus ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiens]</hi> God alone by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is all ſufficient to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: ſo that the leſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary our ſervice is the more neceſſary is it wee ſhould ſerve, if not for Gods ſake, yet for our owne: hee can looſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by us, but wee looſe all things in the loſſe of him.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:1344:6"/>
            <p>And yet ſtrange it is, and wonderfull to conſider thereby with all cheereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to draw us to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, how carefull he hath beene of us, who are yet ſo little uſefull unto him. Looke upon our Creation, when wee firſt came into the world, and you ſhall ſee, that as God made all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures for men, ſo man, becauſe for himſelfe, he would make like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; that as often as wee view our owne ſoules, and ſee whoſe image and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription they have, this might perſwade us to give them up unto God, from whom, and for whoſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice they were firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd. Looke upon our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1344:7"/> preſervation, ſince wee came into the world, and but that,<note place="margin">In Iohan Tract. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quod omni anno fit, aſſiduitate amittit admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth, the continuall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying of theſe great bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings leſſens our admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; with what joy might wee behold the Heavens ſpread over us like a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, the Sun, the Moone, like two unwearied Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, alwayes for our ſakes rejoycing to runne theyr courſe, by vertue of whoſe ſeverall motions and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, while the earth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, Seed-time and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, Summer and Winter, night and day ſhall not ceaſe, that ſo the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the different ſeaſons
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1344:7"/> of the yeare may give us contentment in them all. And if all this be yet too little, looke upon his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for our ſafe conduct to another world, and there behold the word of Life. <hi>The ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere milke of the Word</hi> for children, <hi>ſtrong meate</hi> for men, food co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>venient for us all; behold the Sacraments of life, the ſignes, the ſeales, the pledges of the Love of God; behold the Spirit of life, the power of the Holy Ghoſt overſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſoules, and by an immortall ſeed begetting us again unto a lively hope of immortality: ſurely then well may the eyes of all men waite upon him,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1344:8"/> whoſe <hi>eyes runne through the whole earth,</hi> nay through the whole heaven too, to ſhew themſelves powerfull and gracious unto them that ſerve him.</p>
            <p>And indeed, if we ſhall conſider the ſeverall attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of God how they are fitted to the ſeverall neceſſities of men, this might be a ſtrong perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion alſo to draw us to his ſervice. For God is a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull God, and what more fitting for our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? when the Prince of this world, like the ſtrong man, hath by his ſubtle temptations got footing in our ſoules, unleſſe CHRIST IESVS, the Prince of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Captaine of our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1344:8"/> Salvation, ſhall make re-entry, and caſt him out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; weake and wretched men that we are, who were able to deliver us? God is a wiſe God, and what more fitting for our folly? for <hi>[Melius ſtulti omnes viverent ſi ſervi eſſent ſapientum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. de Vtil. Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi.</note>] Happie were it for all fooles, had they but wiſe Maſters. And when we ſee ſo fooliſh oft-times, are wee ſo ignorant to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the Tree of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge before the Tree of Life; how neceſſary is it, that wee ſhould goe unto Gods Schoole, and there learne, that <hi>this is life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> the perfection of all knowledge, <hi>to know him to be the onely true God, and</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:1344:9"/> IESVS CHRIST, <hi>whom hee hath ſent.</hi> Laſtly, God is a mercifull God, and what more fitting for our ſinne? for every man we know to be a ſinner, every ſinne a tranſgreſſion of the Law, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very tranſgreſſion liable unto a curſe, and this curſe no leſſe then eternall death: how neceſſary is it then that we ſhould ſeeke for a powerfull protection in the ſervice of this Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God, that by his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance we may be able to conteſt, not onely with fleſh and blood, but even with Principalities and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, and ſay with Saint <hi>Paul, Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect,</hi> his elect and faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1344:9"/> 
               <hi>It is God that juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, who is able to condemne us?</hi> Seeing then we are all weake and helpleſſe, and want God as a powerfull protector; we are ignorant and fooliſh, and want him as a wiſe inſtructer; we are wretched and ſinfull, and want him as a mercifull Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: if our duties can not prevaile, may even our neceſſities enforce us, and let every man ſay, and ſay from his heart, <hi>O Lord tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I am thy Servant, I am thy Servant.</hi> And thus much for my firſt obſervation, I come now unto a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As God is our Lord and Maſter, and wee muſt doe him ſervice, ſo this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1344:10"/> ſervice muſt be hearty and ſincere: and therefore wee ſee here, to prevent all ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition of Hypocriſie, the Pſalmiſt bindeth himſelfe with a threefold cord. Firſt we have a profeſſion of his ſervice, <hi>O Lord I am thy ſervant;</hi> ſecondly, we have a repetition of this profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>I am thy Servant, I am thy Servant;</hi> laſtly, we have an aſſeveration affixt unto this repetition, <hi>O Lord,</hi> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>I am thy Servant, I am thy Servant:</hi> and juſtly may we be true and ſincere in our ſervice unto him, who in all his promiſes is ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and faithfull unto us; nay therefore, onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires ſincerity in our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that hee may more
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1344:10"/> faithfully reward us. When one man waites upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that which breeds in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and reluctancie, the wages oftentimes are proportioned, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the worth of the Servant, but the fancie of the Maſter: and ſo we read of LEVVES the eleventh of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">View of <hi>France</hi> page 61.</note> who neglecting men of better abilities, made his Taylor his He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald, his Chyrurgion his Chancellor, his Barber his Ambaſſador;<note place="margin">The <hi>New-Man,</hi> pag. 48.</note> and of Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fift, that he would make no learned Cardinals, leaſt by them his owne ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance might be upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, his Auditor, his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, the Clarke of the Chamber, theſe are the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1344:11"/> Worthies he made choiſe of to fill up his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie. But when man waits upon God, ſo diligent is he in rewarding thoſe who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently ſeek him, that as in his Book all our members, ſo all the ſervice of our me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are recorded; every humble ſigh and groane of the heart, every good word of the mouth, every peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent teare of the eye, every charitable act of the hand ſhall be remembred. He is not like moſt Maſters, who lay the chiefe burden of the worke upon the Servants ſhoulders, &amp; reape the main benefit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves, but where hee gives us Talents to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour &amp; increaſe withall, he requires againe nor Talents
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1344:11"/> nor increaſe; nay, <hi>Quae dat munera muneratur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Salvian. de Gubernat. Dei. lib. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the proportion of the increaſe, ſtill he increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his rewards. For ſo we reade, that when hee who had received five Talents, had gained five more, his Lord requires againe nor principall nor uſe, but to him that hath ſtill ſhall be more given, even uſe upon uſe. <hi>Thou haſt beene faithfull over a few things, I will make thee Ruler over many: enter into thy Maſters joy.</hi> Now who would not gladly w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> all ſincerity ſerve ſuch a Maſter, from whom he may aſſuredly expect the whole benefit, &amp; a thouſand times more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole benefit of his own ſervice? Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1344:12"/> when as wee know that as God hath his different ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, ſome formall, ſome reall, ſo hee hath his dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent rewards too; for formals he hath his forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, his realities for reals. <hi>Seeſt thou not Ahab</hi> (ſayth God) <hi>how he humbleth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> humbleth himſelfe with a temporarie ſorrow, and ſee wee not God how hee requires his humility? <hi>Ahab</hi> is good for a time, and for a time onely God is gracious unto him. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Seeſt thou not my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant Iob, that there is none like him upon the earth, a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and upright man?</hi> and according to the upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Servant, ſee we not the gracious favour of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1344:12"/> his Maſter? As great was his godlineſſe, ſo his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe was great gaine, had the Promiſe of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of this life, after the patient loſſe of his goods, receiving them all double, had the aſſurance of the Bleſſings of the life to come: for <hi>I know,</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>that my Redeemer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth.</hi> Now who would not deſire a thouſand times rather to bee a IOB then an AHAB; and therefore, who would not be carefull to ſerve GOD like <hi>Iob</hi> with a perfect and an upright heart, without which hee knowes it is impoſſible that he ſhould obtaine his deſire? And indeed when, in the ſolemne Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1344:13"/> wee read, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence both of GOD and man, the ſeverall paſſages of pure and undefiled Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion conteyned in this booke of <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> not as expreſſions onely of other mens devotions, but as Patternes of our owne; when wee read, <hi>Lord how doe I love thy Law? It is ſweeter to mee then honey and the honey combe: Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and Evening, and noone-tide doe I pray unto thee, and that inſtantly: As the eyes of the Servants looke upon the hands of their Maſters, ſo our eyes waite up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee O Lord;</hi> And again in my Text, <hi>O Lord, truly I am thy ſervant:</hi> what ſoule trembles not to take theſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1344:13"/> Sacred proteſtations, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome competencie of true Piety and holineſſe, leaſt, if wee had no other witneſſe againſt us, our owne heart might too juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give our tongue the lie? <hi>Will you ſteale,</hi> (ſayth the Prophet) <hi>commit adulterie, and ſweare falſely, and then will you come, and ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me in this houſe?</hi> And then, even then perhaps, when the Conſcience of theſe, or the like ſinnes ſhall cry for vengeance, dare we then ſay? <hi>O Lord, if I have done any ſuch thing, or if there be any wickedneſſe in my hands, then let mine enemy perſecute my life, and take it.</hi> What is this, but ſolemnely to curſe our
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1344:14"/> ſoules, even then when we come to bleſſe them. <hi>Take heed then unto thy foot,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) when thou goeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Houſe of GOD:</hi> for God is holy, and his houſe is holy, and true and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Holineſſe becommeth his houſe for ever. If any man ſhall heere inquire what meaſure of truth and ſincerity wee muſt attaine too, before we can be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of ſo much holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as ſhall preſent us ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto God, this is a queſtion wherein we may better give our ſelves ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction by our piety and prayer, then by our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe: ſo great is the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of ſeverall ages and ſexes, of ſeverall natures
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1344:14"/> and graces, of ſeverall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and educations; that it is impoſſible with ſuch wiſedome and caution, to frame univerſall rules, but that either on the one ſide wee ſhall be too indulgent, or on the other too ſevere: and therefore all the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer I will give you, ſhall be this: When we read in the Goſpell, that <hi>Many are called, but few are choſen,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are called to caſt out de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and propheſie in the name of CHRIST, and by theſe acts ſhall confidently challenge acquaintance of him, who for all this will not vouchſafe to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge them: when wee read of the five fooliſh Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, that they had lamps
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1344:15"/> in their hands, and ſome oyle in their lamps, yet for want of oyle in their veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels too, for want of a full meaſure of that holineſſe, whereof they thought a little quantity would ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, Heaven gates are ſhut againſt them: When wee reade in St. PAVL, that a man may bee <hi>once enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> and yet ſo ſeeing hee may ſee, as that hee can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver truely ſay with SIME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON, <hi>Mine eyes have ſeene thy Salvation;</hi> a man may <hi>taſt of the Heavenly guift,</hi> and yet never ſit downe at the marriage ſupper of the Lambe: Laſtly, when wee read in that great and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day, that CHRIST by his diſcriminating power,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1344:15"/> having ſet the ſheepe on his right hand, ſhall ſet, not only Wolves and Tygers, but even the Goates alſo, men of a more civill and hopefull demeanour at the laſt; judge you, what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men we ought to be in all holineſſe of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, before wee can ever ſincerely take up the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of my Text, <hi>O Lord, truly I am thy ſervant, I am thy ſervant.</hi> And thus much for the ſecond ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, I come now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a third.</p>
            <p>You have ſeene; firſt, that wee muſt ſerve GOD, ſecondly, that wee muſt ſerve him ſincerely; that which now in the laſt place we are to obſerve is, that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1344:16"/> we muſt ſerve him preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>O Lord, truely I</hi> am <hi>thy ſervant.</hi> 'Tis not enough to ſay, Lord, I have beene thy ſervant: for <hi>if any man draw back</hi> (ſayth GOD) <hi>my ſoule ſhall have no pleaſure in him.</hi> 'Tis not enough to ſay, Lord I will be thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; for who knowes what alteration a day may may produce? no, time preſent onely, this is the ſure time: and therefore, <hi>Remember now thy Creator,</hi> (ſayth SALOMON) <hi>I will pay my vowes now,</hi> ſaith DAVID. <hi>Exhort one another dayly, while it is called to day,</hi> (ſaith St. PAVL) and <hi>To day if you will heart his voyce, harden not your hearts.</hi> For, if CHRIST our Maſter be the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1344:16"/> ſame to us <hi>yeſterday, and to day, and for ever,</hi> why ſhould not we his ſervants be the ſame, and reſerve all time for him, not to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row onely but to day? For come and let us reaſon to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; why are we ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to tender our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſervice unto God; can wee ſay, <hi>What profit is it to ſerve the Lord? Doth</hi> IOB <hi>feare God for naught?</hi> It was the confeſſion of the Devill, doth any man feare God for naught? ſurely <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> (ſaith St. PAVL) <hi>it is profitable for all things:</hi> and <hi>Bleſſed is the man</hi> (ſaith DAVID) <hi>that feareth the Lord, thou ſhalt eate the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of thy hands; O well is thee, and happy ſhalt thou be.</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:1344:17"/> Can wee ſay, what plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is it to ſerve the LORD? The beſt wee can reade of Sinne, is that it hath <hi>Pleaſures for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> but the ſervice of God hath <hi>Pleaſures for evermore:</hi> a little Oratorie might ſoone ſuffice to declaime upon all the joyes of the World, but the tongue of Men and Angels is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſet foorth the joyes of the Spirit in the ſervice of our GOD: For <hi>wee rejoyce</hi> (ſayth St. PETER,) <hi>even with Ioy unſpeakable.</hi> And ſurely had wee the power to recall times paſt, and the choyce of what dayes, what houres wee would be pleaſed to live againe; would we deſire a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1344:17"/> reiteration of thoſe earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſenſuall delights, which once to have injoyed hath beene too much? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Impietie it ſelfe durſt not yet bee ſo impious: no rather, what ever <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and peace, and joy in the</hi> HOLY GHOST, what ever <hi>conſolations in</hi> CHRIST, <hi>comforts of Love,</hi> or <hi>fellowſhip of the</hi> SPIRIT, whereof our Conſcience to this day hath preſerv'd the ſweet remembrance: theſe are the acts which being moſt pleaſing to our ſoules, we would be beſt pleas'd to recall. May we then cheerefully goe on in the imbracement of thoſe courſes for time preſent,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1344:18"/> which were we able to call backe time paſt, our owne conſciences beare us wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe wee would willingly make choice of.</p>
            <p>When the Maſter of the Vineyard queſtioned thoſe Labourers hee went to hire, <hi>Why ſtand you all the day idle?</hi> it was ſome excuſe to make anſwer, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no man hath hyred us:</hi> But if wee ſhall ſuffer our Soules juſtly to be charg'd with the ſame queſtion, are we able ſo much as to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the ſame reply? Let us Looke upon our inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that ſolemne ſtipula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when in the waters of regeneration we were firſt conſecrated unto GOD, what promiſes, what vowes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1344:18"/> have beene made in our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe: or if wee dare plead the invalidity of ſuch acts, as have beene performed for us in our nonage, then let us looke, ſince we came to have the knowledge both of good and evill, to have the diſcretion to order our owne wayes, upon the word of God, and the Spirit of God; and if theſe earneſts will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us, that againe and againe wee have beene hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; what anſwer can wee make, if ſtill wee ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be queſtioned, <hi>why ſtand you idle?</hi> Surely, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes thoſe ſinnes are muſt puniſhable, which are moſt inexcuſable. For, what if God let ſome men ſtand
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1344:19"/> idle, and call them not till the laſt houre? What is this to us, who have beene called at the firſt? True indeed it is, that GOD hath his owne li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and calls men at what houre he pleaſe; but it is true withall, that at what houre ſoever he cals us we muſt come. And if in things ſecular wee ſtrive all who ſhall be firſt call'd, to riches, to honour, to the ſeverall contentments of the world; ſhall wee be ſo baſely humble, as not to care, though wee come laſt to be <hi>partakers of the Heavenly calling,</hi> to bee <hi>called to the Saints?</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, when as we know that God in the ſecret
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1344:19"/> councell of his will, as hee hath his ſet times how long hee will call, ſo hee hath his times al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo when upon the ſtop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ping of our eares he calls backe his calls. <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lem, Ieruſalem, hadst thou knowne, at the leaſt in this thy day, the things that belong unto thy Peace: but now they are hidden from thine eyes:</hi> Thou had'ſt once Grace offer'd, when to the comfort of thy Soule thou might'ſt have ſayd. <hi>O LORD, I am thy Servant,</hi> but now no longer will hee be thy Maſter: This happie opportunitie ſhall never be recall'd; <hi>For the dayes come, when thine Enemies
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1344:20"/> ſhall caſt a trench about thee, and lay thee even with the duſt.</hi> And why? <hi>becauſe thou kneweſt not the time of thy viſitation.</hi> The neglect of that happy day wherein they were viſited with Mercy, putteth them off unto the terrible day of the Lord, to the viſitation of his Iuſtice. Now becauſe among many of thoſe wayes of God, which are <hi>unſearchable,</hi> this is one, to obſerve how patient hee is with ſome men, giving them day after day, even to the laſt houre, and yet how quicke hee is with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>come,</hi> come preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>and give an account of thy Stewardſhip;</hi> a thouſand times bleſt is that Soule,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1344:20"/> which every day is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for this great day of account.</p>
            <p>So then to draw all to a concluſion. We reade in the <hi>Revelation</hi> of foure Angels let looſe,<note place="margin">Chap. 9.</note> and no ſooner let looſe, but <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently prepared, for an houre, and a day, and a moneth, and a yeare, to ſley the third part of men.</hi> May we then learne diligence from our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and let not them bee more carefull to deſtroy our Soules, then our ſelves to preſerve them, but may wee all bee prepar'd, at a yeare, at a moneth, at a day, at an houre to ſay, and doe as wee ſay, <hi>O Lord truly I am thy Servant, I am thy Servant. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:1344:21"/>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:1344:21"/>
            <head>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Serm. </seg>II</label> THE SECOND SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>IOHN, 21.22.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>If I will that hee tarry till I come, what is that to thee, Follow thou me.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe Words containe a ſharp anſwer of our SAVIOUR to an indiſcreet, and unſeaſonable queſtion of St. PETER.</p>
            <p>In the handling whereof
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1344:22"/> this order I ſhall obſerve. Firſt, I will indeavour to cleare the difficulty of my Text, and ſhew you what is the meaning of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours anſwer, <hi>If I will that he tarry till I come;</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I will commend unto you ſuch obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as may prove uſefull to our ſelves. To begin then with the firſt, <hi>If I will that he tarry till I come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Expoſition of which conditionall ſpeech of CHRIST, I find great variety among Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Some will admit of no poſitive meaning of the words, but think they were ſpoken onely to put off the inquiſitiveneſſe of PETER, <hi>If I will that he tarry till I
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1344:22"/> come,</hi> or as we uſe to ſay; If I will that hee tarry till doomeſday, what is that to thee? not that he intended that IOHN ſhould tarry till he come, but to ſhew that whether hee tarryed or not tarried, that was nothing to PETER. But this expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if wee marke it, will neither well agree with the phraſe of the ſpeech, nor the wiſdome of the Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. And therefore others there are who do conceive, that whereas St. PETER was to dye of a violent death, and follow his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to the Croſſe, it might be the meaning of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to expreſſe, that no ſuch violence ſhould be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered unto St. IOHN, hee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1344:23"/> ſhould dye of a faire death; fairely and quietly bee bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and ſo <hi>tarry,</hi> and reſt in his grave till CHRISTS comming unto Iudgement. This is an Expoſition, I confeſſe commended by learned Interpreters on all ſides yet ſuch as I cannot be perſwaded to approve; Firſt, becauſe it ſeemeth to ſtraine the phraſe of the Text to an unuſuall ſence, <hi>If I will that he tarry,</hi> that is, <hi>tarry</hi> in his grave. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe thouſands there are who may thus be ſayd to <hi>tarry</hi> till CHRIST com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, when as the ſpeech of our Saviour ſeemes plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to intimate ſomewhat more peculiar unto IOHN. Thirdly, becauſe the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1344:23"/> ground of the Expoſition is very queſtionable. For howſoever certaine it bee that PETER dyed a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent death, yet whether IOHN dyed of a naturall death or no, it may be doubted. Sure I am, that <hi>Polycrates</hi> in <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap</hi> 23.</note> that hee dyed a Martyr; and <hi>Theophylact</hi> confirmeth his ſaying from the words of CHRIST himſelf;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Mat.</hi> 20 23.</note> who ſpeaking of IAMES and IOHN, ſayth expreſly, that <hi>they ſhall drinke of his Cup, and be Baptiſed with his baptiſme.</hi> Now <hi>Iames</hi> wee know drank ſo deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of this Cup, that HEROD <hi>ſtretched foorth his hand and killed him with the Sword:</hi> And, as the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1344:24"/> words of our SAVIOUR doe imply, IOHN muſt pledge him ſo deeply in the ſame Cup, eyther as a Martyr, or at leaſt (as all agree) as a Confeſſor, that in this reſpect the words in my Text cannot ſeeme to conteyne any ſpeciall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of IOHN above PETER, when it is ſayd; <hi>If I will that hee tarry till I come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore a third expoſition there is, which though it be refuſed by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every Commentator; yet I ſhall now indeavour to aſſert it. For I find by often experience that it is with weighing of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as with weighing of gold; that which in one
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1344:24"/> paire of ſcales is thought too light, in another will hold weight. The expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is this; that however as our Saviour had foretold, PETER ſhould more ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily follow him, follow him to the Croſſe and to the grave, he ſhould make no long tarrying here on earth, but goe hence and be no more ſeene; yet it was his will that IOHN ſhould be longer liv'd, live and tarry till hee came, till hee came to execute exemplary judgment on the unbeleeving Iew, in the deſtruction of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, their City, and theyr Temple, till the ſame judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in fearfull manner ſhould attend the ſinnes of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1344:25"/> the Gentiles too, till as the Prophet <hi>Ioel</hi> had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, having firſt come with a gracious and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full offer of his Spirit to be powr'd upon all fleſh, upon the reſiſtance of this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, he ſhould come againe <hi>with wonders in the Heaven, and in the earth, blood, and fire, and pillers of ſmoak.</hi> For the confirmation of which expoſition, three things I ſhall obſerve unto you.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that it is uſuall in holy Scripture, to imply poſitive truths in conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall termes; and it is the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt way in expounding of hard texts, <hi>obſcura de mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt is,</hi> to demonſtrate things obſcure, from the evidence of things manifeſt. Now
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1344:25"/> then manifeſt it is in the ſixt of St. <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 12.</note> when our Saviour ſaith to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples [<hi>Doth this offend you, what and</hi> if <hi>you ſhould ſee the Sonne of man aſcend up where he was before?</hi>] that his meaning is, The time ſhall come, when, to remove this offence, you ſhall ſee the Sonne of man aſcend. Manifeſt againe in the 9. to the Romans.<note place="margin">Verſe 22.</note> when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>[What if God willing to ſhew his wrath?]</hi> that his meaning is. It is the will of God, that he may ſhew his wrath, to indure with long ſuffering, the veſſels of wrath fitted to deſtruction. Manifeſt againe, in the 12.<note place="margin">Verſe 49.</note> of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> when our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſaith,
[<hi>I am come to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1344:26"/> ſend fire on earth, and what will I,</hi> if <hi>it bee already kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led?</hi>] that his meaning is. It is my will, that it ſhall be kindled already. And ſo that when he ſaith here, <hi>If I will that he tarry till I come,</hi> wee may fairely expound this ſpeech with correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence to thoſe others: It is my will and pleaſure that he ſhal tarry til I come.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we finde men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in holy Scripture, of a ſpeciall comming of CHRIST, whereto theſe words in my Text may ſeeme to have ſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference. For wee know that CHRIST is ſayd to come two wayes, eyther in perſon, or in power; in perſon he hath come once
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1344:26"/> already in the fleſh, and at the laſt day will come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in glory. 1. His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in power, is eyther in the power of his grace, for <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I ſtand at the doore and knocke, and if any man heare my voyce and open the doore, I will</hi> come <hi>in, and ſup with him, and he with me;</hi> or in the power of his Iuſtice: and ſo St. IOHN threatens the Church of <hi>Epheſus. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member whence thou art fallen, and repent, or I will come againſt thee ſhortly, and remove the Candleſticke out of his place;</hi> but more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably have we deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed unto us the like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his comming in the 24. of St. <hi>Matthew;</hi> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1344:27"/> intimated in theſe words of my Text. For when the Diſciples ask'd our Saviour, <hi>what ſhall be the ſigne of thy comming, and of the end of the world?</hi> To that which they propoſe, <hi>in ſenſu conjuncto,</hi> in an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſenſe, as beeing falſely perſwaded, that when ever he ſhould come to deſtroy the Temple, then preſently would follow the end of the world too; hee makes anſwer, <hi>in ſenſu diviſo,</hi> in a divided ſenſe; tells them that for the day and houre of his comming in the end of the world, no man ſhould know that: this was a ſecret hidden even from the Angels in Heaven. But as for the day and houre of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1344:27"/> his comming in ſevere and exemplary manner to viſit the ſinnes of the Iewes, and Gentiles alſo, for not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in his name, hereof he gives them a certaine and particular relation: <hi>Nation</hi> ſhall <hi>ſhall riſe againſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Kingdome againſt Kingdome, there</hi> ſhall <hi>be Famines, and Peſtilences, and Earthquakes in divers places,</hi> the <hi>Sunne ſhall bee darkned, and the Moone ſhall not give her light,</hi> and ſuch and ſo <hi>great ſhould be their tribulation in thoſe dayes, as was not from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world:</hi> and that they might not ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put theſe evil dayes farre off, and ſay, <hi>The Lord will delay his comming;</hi> he tells
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1344:28"/> them that within one Age, all theſe things ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen: for verily I ſay unto you, <hi>This generation ſhall not paſſe,</hi> that is, the men of this generation now alive ſhall not all dye, and paſſe away, <hi>till all theſe things be fulfilled;</hi> till they <hi>ſhall ſee the ſigne of the Sonne of man comming with great power and glory.</hi> For ſo we finde, that St. IOHN a man of that Generation, did live and tarry till CHRIST thus came to judge the world; liv'd to ſee the raigne of 13. Emperours of <hi>Rome,</hi> from <hi>Auguſtus</hi> unto <hi>Trajane,</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which time, all thoſe judgments denounced by St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> as the ſignes and effects of CHRISTS
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1344:28"/> thus comming in power were accompliſht.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we may take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the ſingular provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of CHRIST, who intending thus ſhortly to come to judge the world, was yet for the good of his Church, graciouſly pleas'd that St. IOHN ſhould tarry till hee came, and that for theſe three reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt that whereas falſe Teachers were from the beginning crept into the Church, and afterward <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colaitans, Cerinthians, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandrians, Ebionits,</hi> and <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> had corrupted the doctrine thereof, mingling with Chriſtianity the rites of the Gentiles, and the ceremonies of the Iewes,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1344:29"/> ſome denying the truth of CHRISTS humanity, others affirming that he was but a meere man; it pleaſed God that after the departure of all the Apoſtles, St. IOHN ſhould <hi>tarry</hi> &amp; continue, to ſtand as a Pillar to uphold the truth, as an Oracle to be conſulted in all difficulties: and for this cauſe, his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell was laſt written, that in ſuch poynts wherein the former Evangeliſts had not given ſo full ſatisfaction to the Church, his Writings might more perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve them. Secondly, that he might helpe ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the weake faith of the Brethren, amidſt thoſe warres and rumours of warres, amidſt thoſe feares
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1344:29"/> and terrors, which CHRIST was now comming to bring upon the world, and whereof it was his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that his owne choſen, for the tryall of their faith, ſhould beare a part; that when they ſhould ſee, as St. IOHN reports of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that <hi>He</hi> alſo <hi>was their brother and companion in the Kingdome and patience of</hi> CHRIST IESVS, that <hi>He was caſt into baniſhment for for the word and Teſtimony of God,</hi> this might be a ſtrong motive unto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to poſſeſſe their ſoules with patience. For if the beloved Diſciple, hee that lay in the boſome of his Maſter, if he have ſuffered adverſitie, why ſhould any
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1344:30"/> man complaine? Thirdly, whereas (as St. PAVL in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes us) there were even in his dayes, diviſions and ſeparations, <hi>one of Cephas,</hi> and <hi>another of Apollo's,</hi> with Hymnes by themſelves, and Doctrines by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; which diviſions af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards we find by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Heretiques, daily to increaſe (for commonly as men ſide in opinion, they will ſide alſo in affection,) hence was it that St. IOHN tarryed ſo long, tarried if it were poſſible to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all differences, and perſwade the faithfull to <hi>keepe the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.</hi> And therefore it is reported of him, even in his decrepite
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1344:30"/> age, his ſpeech and ſtrength almoſt quite ſpent, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in one word he would epitomize what ever for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly he had more largely preacht unto them, it was his dayly exhortation to his auditors, <hi>Filioli diligite alterutrum, My little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren love one another:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. in cap <hi>6.</hi> ad Galat.</note> and againe, <hi>My little Children love one another:</hi> that if in ſo great diſtraction of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, it was rather to bee wiſht then hop'd for, that they ſhould bee <hi>all of one minde;</hi> yet at leaſt that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent guift of charity, which <hi>beleeves all things, hopes all things, indures all things,</hi> might <hi>hold them in one accord.</hi> And ſurely it is worth the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1344:31"/> obſervation, that the ſame Diſciple whom CHRIST lov'd beſt, is moſt frequent and earneſt in his exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions unto love, to let us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that one princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall effect of Gods love to us, is that wee ſhould love one another? And thus much for the expoſition of my Text: I come now in the ſecond place, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend ſome obſervations to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Where firſt may it pleaſe you to obſerve, that of all the Apoſtles, as wee finde none more commended, ſo none more reprov'd then St. <hi>Peter.</hi> And the reaſon is, becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> was a man of a quicke, active, and zealous ſpirit, ſo forward,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1344:31"/> upon all occaſions, to bee doing, that many times, through the exuberancy of his zeale, hee doth that which is amiſſe. For it is a true rule of the Author <hi>De Vocatione Gentium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas mutabilis, quae non ab in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commutabili voluntate regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, tanto citiùs propinquat iniquitati, quantò acrius in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenditur actioni,</hi> the more earneſtly the mutable will of man, not guided by the incommutable wil of God, is intent upon action, the more prone it is to act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe. To teach us, that the more zealous and active wee are, the more carefull we ought to be in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of our actions, leſt partaking of St. <hi>Peters</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1344:32"/> wee partake of his ſinne too: (though truly) happier is that man who being zealous to doe well, ſhall ſometime doe amiſſe, then hee who for feare of doing ill, will doe nothing at all. Now if we looke into the particulars of PETERS ſinnes, wee ſhall finde one great fault he had, te be given to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion and controll, when it better behooved him to anſwer &amp; obey. When our SAVIOVR in the 16. of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> had declar'd himſelfe that hee <hi>muſt goe up to</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>that hee muſt ſuffer many things of the Scribes and Elders, that hee muſt bee killed and riſe againe the third day,</hi> and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1344:32"/> it had befitted St. PETERS piety to make anſwer with the like prayer which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward his Maſter us'd: O that this <hi>Cup might paſſe from thee, yet not my will, but thy will bee done:</hi> you ſee how imperiouſly hee takes upon him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke and to controll: <hi>Farre bee it from thee, this ſhall not bee unto thee.</hi> When our SAVIOVR had now guirt himſelfe, and told PETER, that he muſt waſh his feet, and it had befitted him in wiſedome, though bee knew not yet the reaſon of this Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, to make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, <hi>Bee it unto mee as thou wilt;</hi> you ſee how in a ſhew of humilitie, hee
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1344:33"/> ſheweth indeed ſome pride and diſobedience, <hi>Thou ſhalt never waſh my feet.</hi> And heere, in this ſtory, when our Saviour ſayth unto him, <hi>Follow thou me,</hi> and it had befitted his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, upon the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance how lately hee had played the run-away, to make anſwer, <hi>Lord I will follow thee whereſoever thou goeſt:</hi> you ſee how preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he forgets himſelfe, and begins to queſtion after <hi>Iohn, Lord what ſhall this man doe?</hi> Now becauſe we know <hi>Peters</hi> infirmities were not his alone, and though wee have warning from him, yet dayly wee are prone to commit the like errors againe; Let me
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1344:33"/> commend unto you that ſober exhortation of St. <hi>Iames, Fratres mei ne ſitis multi magiſtri. My brethren be not many maſters.</hi> Be not too forward to queſtion and controll, what ſhall this man, and this thing doe? and this and this be farre from us, it ſhall not be ſo. For however the great Maſters, in Church and Commonwealth, over our ſoules and bodies, bee not like <hi>Peters</hi> Maſter, have not an infallibility in all the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections they propoſe; yet becauſe ſuch as they are, we are commanded to obey them, and it behoveth our Chriſtian modeſty to bee perſwaded, that they know better how to command
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1344:34"/> us, then we to adviſe them. Let us be very wary upon what termes wee contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict or diſobey; Leſt God in defence of thoſe higher powers, with whom wee are but too prone to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, may give us the like check, which once he gave unto his people Iſrael; <hi>They have not rejected you, but they have rejected me.</hi> Or if there may bee ſome things whereof the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of ſome men cannot bee ſo well perſwaded, (as indeed while men are men, it is not to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in all things that great men ſhould bee Gods) let us not fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heape the coales of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens fires upon our
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1344:34"/> owne heads, and with too much heare and violence make the ſinne of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining, greater than the matter whereof wee doe complain. No, rather when we know, that <hi>there is no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill in the City, which the Lord hath not done,</hi> in all the evils w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> either we feele or feare, let us lift up our eyes unto the Lord for a redreſſe: for certainly with him our humble prayer is able to prevaile more, then tenne thouſand ſtomackfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints. And thus much for my firſt obſervation, I come now unto a ſecond.</p>
            <p>Where in the ſecond place we may obſerve, that however when we read the bare queſtion of St. <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:1344:35"/> our charity might eaſily be ſatisfied, as ſome of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient have conceiv'd, that St. IOHN having heereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore askt at the requeſt of St. PETER, to put the reſt of the Diſciples out of feare, <hi>Lord who is it that ſhall betray thee?</hi> So <hi>Peter</hi> now by way of friendly requitall, that <hi>Iohn</hi> alſo might know his end, and by what death hee was to glorifie God, maketh the like requeſt for him; <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter what ſhall this man doe?</hi> a requeſt wherein admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, of this faire para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe, we may finde mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rather to commend then cenſure him. Yet when we read the anſwer of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, that wee may know
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1344:35"/> he ſeeth not as man ſeeth, he judgeth not as man judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: wheras our ignorance would have ſayd, <hi>We finde no fault in this man,</hi> no ſin in this queſtion: his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge finds as many ſinnes as words. But foure words did <hi>Peter</hi> utter, <hi>Domine hic autem quid?</hi> which wee more largely tranſlate, <hi>Lord what ſhall this man doe?</hi> and yet in theſe foure words there are foure ſinnes. Firſt, a ſin of preſumption, <hi>Lord what ſhall this man doe?</hi> as if CHRIST would have forgotten St. <hi>Iohn,</hi> unleſſe <hi>Peter</hi> had remembred him. Secondly, a ſinne of curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, <hi>Lord, what ſhall this man doe?</hi> as if becauſe <hi>Iohn</hi> knew what ſhould become
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1344:36"/> of <hi>Peter, Peter</hi> muſt needs know what ſhould become of <hi>Iohn.</hi> Thirdly, a ſinne of repining, <hi>Lord, what ſhall this man doe?</hi> as if <hi>Peter</hi> had no mind to follow <hi>Christ,</hi> unles <hi>Iohn,</hi> who had always heretofore beene his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, might goe along with him; and laſtly, a ſin of negligence, <hi>Lord, what ſhall this man doe?</hi> as if it were fitting for him now to inquire after others, when as the ſtrictneſſe of his Maſters charge might have put him in minde ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to looke to himſelfe. All which ſinnes ſeeme to bee expreſt or intimated in the anſwer of our SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIOVR. <hi>If I will,</hi> or it is my will <hi>that hee ſhall
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1344:36"/> tarry till I come:</hi> a check for his Preſumption: Hee ſhall tarry, and you ſhall <hi>follow mee;</hi> a check for his repining? Whether he tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or tarry not, <hi>what is that to thee?</hi> A check for his curioſity; and laſtly, <hi>Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thou me;</hi> which being a repetition of the ſame charge immediatly given him before, implyeth a check for his negligence. So that when we ſee in this caſe of PETER here, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day in our owne que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, our owne anſwers, our owne actions, the caſe may be the ſame; how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sinnes the knowledge of GOD takes notice of, which otherwiſe our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance would never have
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1344:37"/> obſerv'd. He <hi>ſearcheth the heart and reynes,</hi> and weighs each word we ſpeake; how ought this to perſwade us carefully to take heed unto our wayes, to <hi>worke out our Salvation with feare and trembling,</hi> &amp; in ſuch things wherein we think we have done well, ever to bee jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous leſt wee have done ſomewhat amiſſe.</p>
            <p>When wee reade the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Apologies of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> except onely for the foule Sinne of his Denyall, for all other infirmities of <hi>Peter;</hi> Charge him with his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious controlling of his Maſter, oppoſing his own nay unto CHRISTS yea; <hi>This ſhall not be unto thee,</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:1344:37"/> ſo that our Saviour with indignation gives him this ſharpe anſwer, <hi>Get thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind mee Satan;</hi> yet <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> will excuſe him <hi>with an error in ſenſu non af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectu,</hi> though he might erre in his underſtanding, not apprehending the juſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of CHRISTS going to Suffer at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> yet there was no error, (ſayth hee) in the ſincerity of his affection; though in truth great was the error of his affection, ſo to deſire to ſhew his love to CHRIST, as thereby to take a courſe to bereave himſelfe of the benefit of CHRISTS love to him. Charge him with his indiſcreet Petition, wherein the Text expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1344:38"/> that hee <hi>knew not what hee ſaid,</hi> when he ſaid; <hi>Lord, let us heere make three Tabernacles:</hi> hoping, as St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> conceives,<note place="margin">Homil. <hi>57</hi> in Mat.</note> that if hee could have perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Maſter to dwell there, he would never have remov'd to goe and ſuffer at <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> yet <hi>Bellarmine</hi> will excuſe him with a <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit errare, non potuit pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi> Perhaps he might erre, (ſayth hee) but ſurely he could not Sinne; for <hi>hee knew not what he ſaid:</hi> as if it were no ſinne for a man, to ſay, he knowes not what Charge him with his over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confident Proteſtation, as wee ſee afterward by the cowardly event, <hi>Though I ſhould dye with thee, yet
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:1344:38"/> will I not deny thee;</hi> and yet not long after denies him againe and againe, and that before hee was in any danger of death; yet <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> will excuſe him with an <hi>aut nullus hic lapſus, aut amoris exceſſus,</hi> either hee was not to blame at all, or gently to be blam'd onely for an exceſſive expreſſion of his love: though we may eaſily conjecture at the greatneſſe of his ſinne, by the greatneſſe of his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, for if PETER had not ſo boldly offer'd to dye with CHRIST, CHRIST would never have ſuffer'd that he ſhould ſo ſhamefully deny him. Laſtly, charge him with this Preſumptuous, que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulous,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1344:39"/> curious queſtion in the Text; <hi>Lord, what ſhall this man doe?</hi> yet <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> will excuſe him, and of all the Sinnes before mentioned, finde him guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty onely of a little Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſitie, and that with an <hi>If</hi> too, <hi>Si curioſitas dicenda ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia digniſſima,</hi> If you will needs finde him guilty of a little ſinne of curioſitie, ſurely it was but a veniall ſinne. So zealous in all things are they in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of St. PETER, as if his credit were theyr own. Now when wee reade, and heare theſe things, &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at their boldneſs in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſuch ſtrong Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies in his behalfe, as if in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>Peter</hi> had not beene ſo
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:1344:39"/> much to blame for any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of his to be reprov'd, as his Maſter for reproving him; let us beware leſt in the like kinde making the like weake excuſes for our ſelves, we make theyr Sins our owne. Let us beware that we be not too forward to cenſure and controll, to intermeddle with things in Church or State, which are too high for us, to ſpeak e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill of that we doe not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, and then think to excuſe all <hi>with an error in ſenſu non affectu;</hi> if our judgements may be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, yet our affections are well devoted. For it is a great error in mens affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be ſtrong in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of ſuch things
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:1344:40"/> wherein their judgements are but weake. Let not the commonneſs of many ſins cauſe us to give indulgence to our ſelues in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting thereof, becauſe they are ſo common, and then excuſe all <hi>with a potui errare, non peccare,</hi> It was my errour, and <hi>in many things we offend all,</hi> but it was not ſo great a ſin. For ſurely, there is no readier way to make ſinnes great, then thus to leſſen them. And indeed, ſtrange it is to conſider, how juſt and ſtrickt wee are in point of Doctrine, and will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge no ſinne to be veniall; and yet how unjuſt and licentious wee are in point of Practiſe, as if wee
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:1344:40"/> thought few ſinnes to bee mortall. Laſtly, when by the faithfull diſpencers of GODS word, we ſhall often heare our Sinnes anatomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, &amp; multiplyed to more particulars, then wee can ſodainly diſcover, while wee looke upon them only in the groſſe. Let us not breake out into tearmes of indignation, and ſay, <hi>Wee hate theſe men,</hi> becauſe they aggravate our ſinnes, and <hi>Propheſie unto us evill and not good:</hi> No, rather let us hate thoſe Sinnes; for which wee deſerve theſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils. And when we know, that the <hi>heart of man is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull above all things,</hi> and a hard matter it is for any man to know the worſt of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1344:41"/> himſelf, if wee ſhall ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time heare more then our ſelf-indulgence will eaſily beleeve, let us yet bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that wee deſerve more then wee have heard of, and humbly take up the Meditation and Prayer of the <hi>Pſalmist; Who knoweth how oft he offends, O cleanſe thou mee from my ſecret faults.</hi> And thus much for a Second obſervation. I come now unto a third, and I have done.</p>
            <p>And my laſt Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, omitting many others, ſhall bee this; That the great Mercies of GOD are commonly attended with great Iudgements: For therefore, doth our SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIOUR here mention his
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:1344:41"/> comming in my Text; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe having come once already to offer great Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> ſuch as had never beene offered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to offer himſelfe to as many as would beleeve in him that they might not periſh but have everlaſting life; hee intended to come ſhortly againe to ſhew great judgements, ſuch as hee had never ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, judgements ſo much the more ſeverely to be executed, by how much they had beene the more regardleſſe of his Mercies. Thus if you looke backe on the firſt judgements on the Angels. Saint AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVSTINE will tell you,<note place="margin">In Iohan. Tract. <hi>100</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>tantò execrabiliùs beneficii,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:1344:42"/> Dei ingrati, quantò benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiùs ſunt creati,</hi> That the more excellent was the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of theyr Creation, the more execrable was theyr Sinne, the more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, and exemplary was theyr puniſhment, or if ye looke on the firſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon man, the ſame <hi>Auguſtine</hi> will tell you, <hi>Hoc tam leve praeceptum ad obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vandum tantò majori injuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia violatum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Civit. Dei lib. <hi>14.</hi> cap <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quantò facileo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri obſervantia poterat cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diri:</hi> That Gods firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand was with ſo much the greater injuſtice viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, with ſo much the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter juſtice puniſht, by how much with the greater fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitie, and the promiſe of the greater Happineſſe, it
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:1344:42"/> might have been obſerv'd. Thus if we looke upon the Seaven Churches in St. IOHN, as we read a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of great Mercy, the <hi>Tabernacle of GOD came downe among Men,</hi> with <hi>Starres and golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtickes:</hi> So wee heare a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation of great Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments too; <hi>Repent, or I will come and remove the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke,</hi> to the Church of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus: Repent, or I will come and fight against thee,</hi> to the Church of <hi>Pergamos; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, or I will kill thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with death,</hi> to the Church of <hi>Thyatira.</hi> Now when we ſeriouſly conſider what our SAVIOUR ſayth, <hi>Hee that reades theſe things let him underſtand,</hi> and what
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:1344:43"/> St. IOHN hath added, <hi>Hee that hath eares to heare, let him heare what the Spirit ſaith to the ſeaven Churches,</hi> (for the caſe of theſe Churches is a leading caſe for all the Churches of the World;) Let us remember that all theſe things have been ſaid and done to ſerve as enſamples unto us. That ſince the reformation of our Church, great have been the manifeſtations of Gods mercy, great peace, great plenty, and that which is greater then all this, great ſalvation in the free and ſincere diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the great myſteries of Godlineſſe, wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but all thankfully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge. And if my
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:1344:43"/> obſervation (as certaine it is) be true, that great judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments attend great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, upon the neglect of ſo great Salvation, that great Viſitations will enſue wee cannot but be afraid. But yet it is not for mee to tell you the times and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of thoſe judgements, which God hath reſerved in his owne power. For as the exhalations ariſing from the Earth and Seas, wee all know to bee the cauſe of thoſe clouds which produce raine and ſtormes, yet no man dares take upon him to aſſure, That this day, or this houre it will raine, or this moneth, this yeare will bee a great flood:
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:1344:44"/> So though wee know the exhalations of our ſinnes rayſe clouds of ſeparation betweene GOD and us, yet how long theſe clouds will be gathering together be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they produce a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſtorme, it exceeds the apprehenſion of man to be able to determine. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed hitherto, whether in the courſe of our Religion in this laſt Age, there have been ebbes or flowes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee have increaſt or diminiſht the talents God hath given us, though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men raſhly take upon them to give judgement, yet I think it is not ſo eaſie a matter to decide. And becauſe in this argument e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man almoſt preſumes
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:1344:44"/> to ſpend his conjecture, I hope the commonneſſe of the Preſumption will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me, if I ſhall diſcover mine. And for my part I am perſwaded, that there is no ſuch <hi>iniquity in Iacob,</hi> no ſuch <hi>tranſgreſsion</hi> in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> no ſuch tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on exceeding the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of our Fathers, even in the beſt times that can be nam'd, that for this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wee ſhould have any more cauſe then they to feare, that God who hath hitherto come graciouſly to us <hi>with his Love,</hi> ſhould now ſhortly bend his bow and whet his Sword, and come upon us <hi>with the Rod.</hi> Neceſſary I confeſſe it is, that with the declaring of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:1344:45"/> GODS juſt judgements un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinners, wee ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten threaten and humble the Soules of men; but yet ſo farre to diſhearten the Lords people with the feare of generall imminent viſitations, as to bring them into diſlike of the Church and State wherein they live, to occaſion them to remove by hundreds and thouſands into remote and deſolate parts of the world, as if they could any where bee more ſafe then where they are; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this is a point of zeale ſtrain'd ſo farre beyond diſcretion, that I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded GOD himſelfe doth not approve it. 'Tis poſſible I confeſſe on the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:1344:45"/> one ſide <hi>to daube with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered morter,</hi> and ſay; <hi>Peace, peace, when there is no peace;</hi> but on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide let mee tell you, 'Tis not impoſſible for men to make ZEDECHIAS hornes, and ſay; Thus, and thus ſhall the Lord puſh, when the Lord hath not ſent them, and thereby as the Prophet complaines, <hi>make the heart of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 13.22.</note> 
               <hi>whom the LORD hath not made ſad.</hi> For mine own part, as long as wee are not able (and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be GOD that wee are not able) to demonſtrate the like ſinnes of Idolatry, cruelty, injuſtice, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, wherwith God by all the Prophets chargeth
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:1344:46"/> his people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> before e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hee threatens to come and viſit them; I cannot be perſwaded, that any man hath juſt warrant to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the like judgements againſt us. And thus farre have I declar'd my ſelfe, not that I would flatter the Times, or footh men up in theyr tranſgreſſions; for wee know, that every day God for ſingle ſinners hath ſingle viſitations, though the great and terrible day of his Wrath be never ſo farre off. What? becauſe wee feare not any judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the whole Land, ſhall any Sinner therefore not be afraid of judgement on himſelf? This is, as if a Soldier in the warres, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:1344:46"/> himſelfe ſafe from the Cannon, ſhould therefore deſperatly runne upon a volly of ſmall ſhot, when as we know a little Piſtoll will kill a man, as well as a great Ordnance. But thus much have I ſpoken for three cauſes. Firſt, that I might adviſe men to bee more wary in theyr com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative invectives againſt Sinne. For <hi>cry aloud and ſpare not, tell Iudah of his ſinnes, and Iſrael of his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greſsions:</hi> but ſhall wee therefore, to the heavie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the government of the State, and if the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation were true, to the inexcuſable diſhonour of our owe profeſſion, to whoſe charge the Soules of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:1344:47"/> men are committed, if we that are appointed to build up ſhall ſuffer them to fall downe; ſhall wee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſay, never more ſinne, never more tranſgreſſion, never more feare of CHRISTS comming un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Iudgement? For who hath kept a booke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance? who knowes how oft wee have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended? or who knowes how oft out Fathers have offended? Nay, who knowes but that GOD may bee offended for want of our thankfulneſſe for the increaſe of his grace and favor toward us, which we will not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to acknowledge? Secondly, that I might a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:1344:47"/> little moderate the zeale and paſſions of men: For as wee are equally behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the motion and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the Moone, if that bee the ſecond cauſe, ſometime for withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the waters to an ebbe, as well as ſometime for raiſing them up unto a flood: ſo ſurely it is as commendable an act, though not ſo popular, ſometime to allay the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of men, when they begin to overflow, as well as ſometime to raiſe and ſtirre them up, when they are at a low ebbe. And indeed, if the minds of men bee once ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded, that day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the World growes
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:1344:48"/> worſe and worſe, every man will take upon him to finde out the cauſe, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable it were, would they only conceive in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, that the <hi>Imaginations of the heart of Man were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually</hi> proner and proner unto <hi>evill,</hi> but when they preſume to goe on unto particulars, and one poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the Doctrine, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the diſcipline of the Church, one at the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, another at the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours both in Church and Common-wealth; this is that, which in time may bring all unto confuſion, and with their owne hands help, to pluck downe thoſe Iudgments, which they pretend to be moſt carefull
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:1344:48"/> to keepe off: when as if the minds of men were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded better things, and ſuch as accompany ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, would they beleeve that it is with our Religion as with our wealth, though many men be <hi>miſerable, and poore, and naked,</hi> yet for the moſt part there is more gold, more ſilver, more precious ſtones, more knowledge, more piety, more men that have given up their names to CHRIST; this might be a ſtrong mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to retaine them in a good opinion of the Church and ſtate wherein they live, &amp; to cauſe them to confeſſe with IACOB, <hi>Surely the Lord was in this place, and we were not aware
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:1344:49"/> of it.</hi> Laſtly, that this may ſerve as a ſpurre to our Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and devotion, and cauſe us thus to diſpute and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue with our ſelves, Doth Religion daily grow up from ſtrength to ſtrength, and ſhall I ſtand onely at a ſtay? Is there every where more underſtanding, more plentifull meanes of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the free and ſincere diſpenſation of the Word and Sacraments, and ſhall I bee a ſtranger in Iſraell, and know little or nothing of theſe things? Have the <hi>hyred Servants in my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe now bread enough and ſhall I periſh for hunger?</hi> And indeed, what ſtronger argument to perſwade us to be proficients in Chriſts
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:1344:49"/> Schoole, then to ſee and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the towardli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our fellow ſchollers.</p>
            <p>So then to draw all to a concluſion, We read in the booke of <hi>Numbers,</hi> when BALAK requeſted BALA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AM, <hi>Come curſe me</hi> IACOB, <hi>and come and defie Iſraell,</hi> that BALAAM returnes him anſwer from the mouth of GOD, <hi>How ſhall I curſe, whom</hi> GOD <hi>hath not curſed, or how ſhall I defie, whom the Lord hath not defied?</hi> Thus in the handling of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon place of CHRISTS comming unto Iudgment, if the heate of ſome mens zeale ſhall call upon mee to curſe IA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COB, and defie <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and in the voyce of thunder
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:1344:50"/> threaten the ſuddaine exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions of Gods wrath, my faire anſwer is, <hi>How can I curſe</hi> whom, from my heart I am perſwaded, <hi>God hath not curſed,</hi> or <hi>how can I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, whom the Lord hath not defied?</hi> All that I will ſay is this, that as the generall goodneſſe and religion of this Land may cauſe us, according to the wonted mercies of Almighty God, to conceive a faire hope, that there are no generall viſitations neare at hand, ſo I beſeech you, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to vindicate the not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable truth of ſo good a Paradox, let mee crave the ayd of your Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to make a ſtrong party againſt any man that ſhall
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:1344:50"/> oppoſe us, and let each ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle man in ſingleneſſe of heart, be ſo carefull of his owne particular, that wee may all daily <hi>preſent our ſelves as a living Sacrifice, holy and acceptable unto God,</hi> that wee may <hi>come behind</hi> our Fathers <hi>in no guift,</hi> that we <hi>may bee confirmed unto the end,</hi> and <hi>found blameleſſe at the comming of our Lord</hi> IESVS CHRIST. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:1344:51"/>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:1344:51"/>
            <head>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Serm. </seg>III</label> THE THIRD SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IOHN, 1.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>And Grace for grace.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the fulneſſe of time was come,</hi> ſo <hi>God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the World, that hee ſent forth his owne Sonne;</hi> and (that which ſets forth the rareneſſe of this Love) in this fulneſſe of time, when
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:1344:52"/> the fulneſſe of Sinne did now cry for the full vyals of GODS wrath, behold! where Sinne abounded, Grace did much more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound;<note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> GOD <hi>ſent forth his Sonne, full of Grace and Truth.</hi> And that this ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his might not ſerve to upbraid the empty world, and to condemne it, but that the world ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by might be ſaved; it was not onely <hi>Plenitudo abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantiae,</hi> a filling fulneſſe; but <hi>plenitudo redundantia,</hi> a flowing fulneſſe: For, <hi>of his fulneſſe have wee all recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and Grace for grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words, two Parts in the generall may bee obſerved: Firſt, the Fountaine of bliſſe, from
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:1344:52"/> whence all Happineſſe is derived to us, <hi>Of his ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe have wee all received:</hi> and ſecondly, in my Text, the ſtreames which flow from this Fountaine, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to us by way of excellencie in the emphaſis of this little particle <hi>And, Of his fulneſſe have wee all received:</hi> And that of no ordinary common fulneſſe, nay not onely, <hi>Truth for truth,</hi> a great happineſſe to know our Maſters will; but that then which the goodneſſe of the Father hath vouchſafed heere no greater bleſſing to his own Sonne, <hi>Grace for grace;</hi> that by the fulneſſe of <hi>Truth,</hi> knowing the will of our heavenly Father, by
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:1344:53"/> the fulneſſe of <hi>Grace,</hi> wee may bee ſo happie to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill it.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe the words of my Text will hardly be divided, for they are coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>grace;</hi> it ſhall ſuffice me to make a diviſion of the ſence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and three expoſitions there are, all concurring to make one compleat Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie, which ſhall ſerve mee in ſtead of ſo many Parts; in the handling whereof, I hope I ſhall not need to crave your attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſurely, the very name of <hi>Grace,</hi> the moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bleſſing, which, next unto his Sonne; GOD ever gave unto his Saints, will challenge it; and upon the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:1344:53"/> delivery of ſo happie an Ambaſſage from Heaven ſolicite your thoughts with the like meditation, which old ELI put into the month of SAMUEL, <hi>Speake LORD, for thy ſervant heareth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then three Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions there are, and the firſt is this: <hi>Of his fulneſſe have wee all received, and Grace for grace;</hi> that is, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Graces, ſome one grace ſome another: For, as no man hath receiv'd the fulneſſe of CHRIST, but of his fulneſſe onely, ſo of his fulneſs every man receives not grace alike, but Grace for grace. <hi>Though the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit be the ſame, and the ſame Lord,</hi> (ſayth St. PAVL,) <hi>yet
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:1344:54"/> there are diverſities of gifts, and difference of adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and GOD hath ſet in his Church ſome Prophets, ſome Apoſtles, ſome Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, ſome Interpreters.</hi> For the Church of CHRIST is a myſticall body; and <hi>a Body</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>is not one member but many.</hi> And as in the Naturall body all motion, the Phyſitian will tell you, comes from the Head, and yet every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber hath a different motion by it ſelfe; So in our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall head CHRIST IESVS wee all live and move, and have our being, and yet divers are the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the different mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this body.<note place="margin">Minut. Faelix.</note> 
               <hi>Simil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> univerſi videmur, &amp; tamen
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:1344:54"/> diſsimiles inter ſe univerſi invenimur.</hi> As in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſo in the Soules of men alſo, there is a kind of unlike likeneſſe; and not onely in the graces of illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, but of Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation too, every man al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt hath a different mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of one and the ſame Spirit. <hi>In my Fathers houſe</hi> (ſayth CHRIST) <hi>there are many manſions,</hi> as in his upper Houſe of glory many manſions, ſo in his lower houſe of Grace alſo many manſions: Some, wee ſee, more humble, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers more temperate, ſome more devout, others more charitable, ſome more mercifull, others more juſt. In ABRAHAM wee
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:1344:55"/> reade the ſingular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of Faith; in IOB, of Patience; in MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SES, of Meekneſs; in PHI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NEES, of Zeale; not that thoſe graces are infus'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but oft-times emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent alone. For as a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, which enlightens the whole roome within, ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth onely through the window to thoſe which are without; ſo in divers men there are different kinds of clariſtories, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the graces of GOD which inlighten the whole Soule within, doe yet but in part ſhine foorth to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <hi>Et qui non habet om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. Dialog. adverſ. Paelageum.</note> 
               <hi>non condemnatur ex eo quod non habet, ſed juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur ex eo quod poſſidet.</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:1344:55"/> And hee that wants the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minencie in himſelfe of many a commendable ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in another man, ſhall not bee condemn'd for what hee hath not, but ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified rather for what hee hath. <hi>Vnum iter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. Epiſt. <hi>11.</hi> ad Ageru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiam.</note> 
               <hi>at perve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niendi quò cupias multa com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendia.</hi> For though there bee but one high-way to Heaven, yet there are many pathes therein. IOHN BAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIST came neyther eating nor drinking, the Sonne of man came eating and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: and yet both came the right way. Surely then the way to Heaven is not ſo narrow, but that in reſpect of the different expreſſions of one and the ſame Grace, wee may
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:1344:56"/> walke thither as well hand in hand, as ſtep after ſtep. To give you a quicke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the preſent affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many vertuous and good men. For as no man is ſo farre to ſequeſter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from the publique af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, but even in the moſt private condition is to labour and pray that we may all leade a peaceable and quiet life in all godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and honeſty, to joy or grieve, according as the happie or unhappie ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of things ſhall mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter juſt cauſe; So I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelf many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands there are of piouſly devoted men, ſome who mourne to behold the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:1344:56"/> ſtreames of ungodlineſſe over-flowing the Soules of a world of men, and how farre the beſt come ſhort of the perfection of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, whereto the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of that Truth which wee profeſſe directs us: and yet ſome againe who doe rejoyce, to ſee, amidſt a crooked and froward ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, how many names there are yet every where given up unto GODS ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, to ſee the free and ſincere acknowledgement of that Sacred truth, the zealous and painfull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation whereof daily produceth happie effects of righteouſneſſe, and peace, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt, more perhaps then in five
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:1344:57"/> times ſo great a circuit in any part of the whole Chriſtian world. And ſurely what ever, for what cauſes ſoever, may be our owne apprehenſion of our own condition, when time ſhall have buried all theſe ſmall occaſions in forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, Poſterity will live to make an honourable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance even of theſe dayes of ours, which our ingratitude can now hardly mention but with ſpleene. Now then, ſhall hee that mournes ſay, Woe be to you that rejoyce? Or ſhall hee that rejoyceth, deſpiſe the ſorrow of the mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner? No ſurely, are they not both Brethren, why then ſhould they ſtrive?
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:1344:57"/> Godly joy and godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, they are but Grace for grace, both different effects of one and the ſame Spirit. As then upon the view of the ſecond Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the Story tels us many <hi>wept with a loud voyce,</hi> and many <hi>ſhowted aloud for Ioy,</hi> all equally affected to the good and welfare of that State; ſo now whether we mourne for the happineſs wee want, or joy in the preſent happineſſe we doe injoy, let us give each to other the right hand of fellowſhip; and in our daily Prayers ſalute both Church and State in the language of my Text, and ſay <hi>Grace, grace unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:1344:58"/>
            <p>Againe, as in divers men there are different kinds of Grace, ſo different de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees too; there are Babes, and there are men in CHRIST, and there is milke for babes, and ſtrong meat for men. For the Church of GOD (ſaith St. PAVL) is like to a <hi>great houſe,</hi> and <hi>in a great houſe there are not onely veſſels of gold and ſilver, but veſſels of wood and earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as in zeale we are all to indeavour to be made of the beſt mettle, ſo in charity wee are to hope well of the worſt too, leſt the veſſell of ſilver, while it ſmites a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the veſſell of clay, ſtriving to breake that,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:1344:58"/> may bruiſe it ſelfe. <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus Dei ſuper aquas fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. Ocean. cap <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; naſcentem mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum partunebat,</hi> The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God mov'd, not onely upon the high Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, but the low waters too; and as we read in the Creation, that <hi>God call'd the light Day,</hi> and <hi>the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Night;</hi> yet when hee joynes them both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the denomination followes the better part, and <hi>the Evening and the Morning make a Day;</hi> ſo in the Soules of many men, though there be evening as well as morning, darkeneſſe as well as light, though there bee great diſobedience, if there be great repentance
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:1344:59"/> too; Such is the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Almighty GOD, as that the darkneſſe ſhall be ſwallowed up of light, and the Evening and the Morning make a Day. Where GOD ſowes plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully hee expects plenty, and where hee ſowes ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly hee is content ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly to reape: for five Talents perhaps he would not have been pleas'd with the increaſe of foure more, and yet for two hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts two. For as the Church of GOD is like IACOBS ladder, though none but Angels climbe it, yet there are ſome aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſome deſcending, ſome above, ſome below, and all upon the Ladder;
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:1344:59"/> ſo the Grace of GOD it is like Manna in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe. So ſtrict an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actor is hee of the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of all that wee can doe, as that hee that ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers much, ZACHA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIE and ELIZABETH, who all theyr life long fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red GOD and walked blameleſs, ſhall have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing over, no workes of Supererrogation, no Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for the Church; and yet ſo mercifull is hee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe on whom he will have Mercy, as that hee that gathers little, the Thiefe upon the Croſſe, not till his laſt houre bethinking himſelfe of his laſt end, though hee take up but a ſhort <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento;
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:1344:60"/> Remember me when thou commest into thy Kingdome,</hi> ſhall have no lacke.</p>
            <p>Let not him then that is now reaching the top of the Ladder, deſpiſe him, who perhaps is yet but on his knees humbly creeping to the foot. Let not the tall Cedar, who once himſelfe hee knoweth was but a broken Reede, for what hath hee which hee hath not received, let him not fall heavie on the ſmoaking Flax. For even babes in CHRIST, they are the children of GOD, and may live to become Men; and where the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke is not able to digeſt ſtrong meate, life a while
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:1344:60"/> may bee maintain'd with milk. You know what a ſmart anſwer our SAVIOVR gave St. PETER, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of good will he was but a little inquiſitive after IOHN, <hi>Maſter what ſhall hee doe? What's that to thee? follow thou mee.</hi> Surely then, what excuſe ſhall wee make, who not onely by way of inquiſition, but by way of cenſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, as any mans life and actions, nay (ſuch is the touchineſſe of this waſpiſh age) but his opinion onely ſhall but a little thwart us, preſently wee give him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, with a Lord what ſhall become of this man, when as indeed the conſcience of our owne infirmities might
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:1344:61"/> farre better buſie our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations to inquire, <hi>Lord, what ſhall become of mee?</hi> and I could wiſh that gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſentence of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then were imprinted in the heart of every Chriſtian; <hi>Optimum ego et emendat iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum exiſtimo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plin. l. <hi>8.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>qui caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ita ignoſcit, tanquam ipſe quotidie peccet; ita pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catis abſtinet, tanquam ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini ignoſcat.</hi> Hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is a right good man, who in all things is ſo favourable to the ſinnes of others, as if himſelfe were the greateſt ſinner; and yet ſo ſevere and ſtrict unto himſelfe, as if hee would favour no man. And thus much for the firſt expoſition of my
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:1344:61"/> Text, I come now unto the ſecond.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And of his fulneſſe have wee all received,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and grace for grace:</hi> that is, grace upon grace, grace after grace, firſt one grace then another. For GOD who gave not the Spirit by meaſure to his Sonne, gives it by meaſure and portions to his Saints; which like good ſeed ſowne into good ground brings foorth firſt the blade, then the eare, then the full corne in the eare; firſt the will, and then the deed; firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins the deed, and then perfects it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>give diligence,</hi> ſaith St. PETER, <hi>and adde to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:1344:62"/> your faith vertue, to vertue knowledge, to knowledge temperance, to temperance patience, to patience godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> and that wee may know there are many and high degrees to bee aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded before we come unto the height of grace, to that full aſſurance, whereof fondly oftimes we ſecure ourſelves even at the firſt ſtep, you ſee againe he dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles the ſame caution; <hi>Give diligence to make your calling and Election ſure.</hi> And St. PAVL often, <hi>Let the word dwell richly in you, in all wiſedome; Let your love abound more and more, That you may bee rooted, and built up, and ſtabliſhed in the faith; That you may be holy
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:1344:62"/> and unreproovable in the ſight of God; That hee may preſent unto himſelfe a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Church, not having ſpot or wrinkle.</hi> Indeed it is the deſire of moſt men, to be partakers of Gods grace, ſo much at leaſt as may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten them a little, give them a taſte of the heavenly guift, and keepe them from deſpaire; and then are they ready to ſay unto theyr ſoule, <hi>Soule take thy eaſe:</hi> for thou haſt now enough, grace enough, layd up in ſtore. But the earneſt and conſtant deſire of grace for grace, and grace upon grace, to follow our Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as St. HIEROM did (with a <hi>peto ut acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piam, &amp; cum accepere rurſus
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:1344:63"/> peto,</hi>) dayly doe I aske the grace of God,<note place="margin">Avarus ſum ad ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipienda beneficia dei. Nec ille deficit in dando, nec ego ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiendo. Ad Cteſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor. adv. Pelag.</note> and when I have obtain'd what I aske for, dayly doe I aske the ſame againe, and as long as hee is well pleaſed to grant, never will I give o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my deſire; this a rare zeale: though yet in truth better have no talent, then wrap it in a Napkin. For GOD will not bee content with his owne, hee muſt have intereſt; where hee ſoweth grace, he expects to reape grace for grace: and therefore having once ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of the heavenly guift, let us dayly ſo hunger and thirſt after Righteouſneſſe, as that wee may bee filled with the Spirit.</p>
            <p>For wee are to obſerve,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:1344:63"/> that as in GOD there is a fulneſſe, if I may ſo ſpeak, of capacitie, fulneſſe of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, fulneſſe of mercy, fulneſſe of wiſedome, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of power, all fulneſſe at the full, becauſe hee is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely full; as in CHRIST there is a fulneſſe of ſatie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſuch a fulneſſe as was fitted and proportioned by the will of his Deitie, ſuch a fulneſſe as did abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatiate the will and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of his humanitie; a fulneſſe without meaſure, if compar'd to that ſmall portion vouchſafed to the greateſt of the Saints: and yet a fulneſſe which had meaſure and proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if compar'd unto the infinite fulnes of the Deity.
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:1344:64"/> 
               <hi>Deus quamvis omnipotens non potuit vel inaequalem ſibi gignere filiis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard. Homil. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>vel aequalem condere creaturam.</hi> It was impoſſible that even the omnipotencie of GOD, ſhould eyther beget the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine perſon of his Sonne unequall, or create his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature equall to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: ſo in tne Saints of God there muſt bee a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe too, a fulneſſe of competency, fulneſſe of Faith, and fulneſſe of workes alſo, that while we beleeve in him who ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth a ſinner, wee may daily labour the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſinnes. <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith CHRIST, <hi>I ſtand at the doore and knocke: and if any man heare my voyce, and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:1344:64"/> open the doore, I will come in, and ſup with him, and hee with me.</hi> Here then you ſee there muſt bee a mutuall entertainment of ſupper for ſupper, fulneſſe for ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for indeed then one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is this Feaſt rightly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, when as well CHRIST ſuppes with us, as we with him, he on the delight of our obedience, we on the confidence of his.</p>
            <p>True indeed it is, that if wee looke into the empty world, a little goodneſſe may ſoone raiſe us unto a Phariſaicall oſtentation, and ſerve to juſtifie our ſelves by negatives, <hi>Lord I thanke thee,</hi> that I am not thus nor thus, nor like
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:1344:65"/> unto this Publicane; and thinke that wee have grace enough, if wee can poynt out any man more grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe then our ſelves; when as yet St. AVGVSTINE will tell us,<note place="margin">Civit. dei, l. <hi>14.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ipſe diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus non eſt fornicator, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ebrioſus,</hi> the Divell himſelfe might thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend himſelfe, for he was never drunke, nor ever committed Fornication; and the Publicane might make reply. LORD I thanke thee that I am no Phariſee, when as perhaps his whole life hath beene ſo farre from expreſſing the truth of godlineſſe, as that hee was never yet ſo well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to make ſhew of it.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:1344:65"/> 
               <hi>Infaeliciſsimum genus conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationis eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Salvian. ad Eccleſ. Cathol. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>de miſeriis homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num peccatorum capere ſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</hi> It is a moſt unhappy kinde of comfort, for a man to ſolace himſelfe in his owne ſinne, upon the view of greater ſinnes in others; No, rather letting paſſe theſe deceivable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, let us ſtrive to faſhion our ſelves accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the infallible rules of holy Scripture: and when wee know they are no common graces of the Spirit, whereby wee are ſeal'd unto the day of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; let us dayly implore <hi>grace for grace,</hi> that wee may <hi>approve the things that are excellent, and bee filled with the fruits
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:1344:66"/> of righteouſneſſe. Nativitas ſalutaris non accepta ſed cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodita vivificat:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyprean Epiſt. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> It is not a ſingle grace, but grace upon grace muſt ſave us: and however the goodneſſe and mercy of God might bee content with leſſe, then our owne care and zeale will bee content for our owne ſelves; however our ſelves in humility might be content with the loweſt roome, even to bee doore-keepers in the houſe of God: yet how unſpeakable would bee our joy, if it might pleaſe him to grant more, then wee dare pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ask, and according to our increaſe in grace for grace, multiply unto us glory for glory too, and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:1344:66"/> entertaine us in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, with an <hi>Amice aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende ſuperiùs, Friend ſit up higher:</hi> As then IACOB returning into his owne Countrey, and afrayd of his brother ESAV, ſends be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him preſent after pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, firſt Goates, then Ewes, then Rammes, then Camels, and commands every Meſſenger to ſay; <hi>Theſe are thy ſervant</hi> IA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COBS, <hi>and it is a preſent ſent to my Lord</hi> ESAV; that if the firſt preſent could do nothing, the ſecond, the third, or fourth, might move him; and thus where he feared moſt, hee findes moſt love, ESAV <hi>imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth him, falles upon his neck and kiſſeth him:</hi> ſo let it be
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:1344:67"/> all our care, being how on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward on our way to <hi>ſeeke a Countrey,</hi> and bow ſoone wee may meet with our LORD wee cannot tell, to ſend before us preſent after preſent, grace after grace; that when hee ſhall meet heere with our patience, there with our humilitie, here with our prayer, there with our repentance, heere with our faith, there with our charity; hee may em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace us in the armes of his mercy, and incourage our trembling ſoules with a <hi>Confide fili, Be of a good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort my Sonne, thy ſinnes are forgiven thee.</hi> And thus much for the ſecond expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, I come now unto the laſt.</p>
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:1344:67"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Of his fulneſſe have wee all received,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 <hi>Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition:</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and grace for grace,</hi> that is grace to us anſwerable to the grace of CHRIST; not hee one grace wee another, but grace for grace, grace in ſome proportion of like nature, like condition with his. GOD <hi>is faithfull,</hi> ſaith St. PAVL, <hi>by whom wee are called into the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of his Sonne, who when wee were dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes, hath by the ſame ſpirit quickened us together with</hi> CHRIST, <hi>hath rais'd us up together, made as ſit together in heavenly places.</hi> And indeed it is a medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation full of comfort, that all thoſe graces and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors imparted to CHRIST
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:1344:68"/> the head, are communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to us his members, <hi>of his fleſh, and of his bones.</hi> Was hee ſaluted with that gracious voyce from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>This is my beloved Sonne, in whom I am well pleaſed:</hi> behold the ſame ſpirit, though ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yet powerfully cryes, <hi>Abba Father</hi> in our ſoules, and aſſures us that wee alſo are the <hi>Sonnes of God,</hi> nay <hi>heyres,</hi> yea <hi>coheyres</hi> with his owne Son. For as CHRIST was incarnate and made the Sonne of God by aſſuming our nature to his perſon; ſo there is a kinde of incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in every Saint of God, by uniting his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to our perſons. And indeed every pious Soule
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:1344:68"/> is another Virgin MARY, wherein wee reinwombe our SAVIOVR,<note place="margin">Qui par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turit ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bam Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turit. Amb in Luc. lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> and with whom wee travaile till hee be formed in us, til he who is conceived in us, is the Author of our new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, and giveth ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all life and motion to our ſoules. Had hee the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull grace and power to worke great miracles, give eyes to the blinde, ſpeech to the dumbe, health to the ſicke, life to the dead? <hi>Hee that beleeves in me,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the workes that I doe, ſhall he doe alſo, nay even greater workes then theſe ſhall hee doe.</hi> For if wee faile of the ſhadow, in the practiſe of thoſe great workes upon the body; yet we have the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:1344:69"/> ſubſtance of farre greater works upon the ſoule. And ſuch to this day, is the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull efficacie of this quickning grace, as that it openeth the blind eye, and the deafe care, with joy to behold and heare the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull workes of God; it looſeneth the dumb to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue, and out of the mouths of babes and ſucklings, ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſtrength; it ſtretcheth forth the lame hand, with cheerfulneſſe to diſtribute to the neceſſities of others; it ſofteneth the hard heart, and kindleth it with zeale and forwardneſſe, <hi>O Lord, my heart is ready, my heart is ready.</hi> Nay though wee bee dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes, grace is able to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:1344:69"/> us. <hi>Awake thou that ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, and ariſe from the dead, and</hi> CHRIST <hi>ſhall give thee light.</hi> Laſtly is CHRIST aſcended up to Heaven, <hi>farre above all Principalities and Powers,</hi> there for ever to ſit at the right hand of the Father, and will hee leave us comfortleſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone? No ſurely, as hee hath given us grace for grace, ſo will hee give us glory for glory too, and therefore <hi>Bleſſed bee GOD,</hi> ſayth St. PETER, <hi>who hath begotten us againe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a lively hope, by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of</hi> IESVS CHRIST, <hi>from the dead, to an inheritance incorruptible, reſerved for us in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:1344:70"/>
            <p>Now hitherto, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelfe we all glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give eare to this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and are ready to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond it with the like Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Diſciples, <hi>Lord evermore give us of this grace.</hi> But yet I feare that as DAVID, who went with joy to fetch the Arke out of the houſe of AMINA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, on expectation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by of a bleſſing to befall his owne houſe, when hee ſaw VZZAH ſmitten with ſodaine Death, for preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to touch the Arke, was preſently diſpleas'd, and afraid too, for <hi>how ſhall the Arke of the Lord,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>come to me?</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſent it to the houſe of OBED EDOM. So I
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:1344:70"/> feare many there are well pleaſed with the grace of CHRIST, as long as wee diſcourſe of the joy, the comfort, the glory that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it: but let us once mention the ſorrow and affliction which for grace and righteouſneſſe ſake we muſt endure: let us tell them that he that will bee CHRISTS Diſciple, muſt firſt in humility <hi>deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> and with patience <hi>take up his Croſſe and follow him:</hi> this is a hard ſaying, ſay they, and who is able to endure it? If theſe bee the difficulties which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Ark, let it goe to the houſe of OBED EDOM, we will not bring it to our City. But before you
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:1344:71"/> ſend it away, let mee aske you but one queſtion, <hi>ſhall we receive good at the hands of the Lord, and ſhall wee not receive evill?</hi> nay more, <hi>Is it not enough that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple bee as his Maſter, and the Servant as his Lord?</hi> Would wee receive grace, and will we not have grace for grace? would wee have the grace of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation, and will wee not have the grace of his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie? CHRIST him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wee know <hi>firſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> before hee <hi>entred into glory;</hi> and wee muſt firſt bee made <hi>conformable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his death,</hi> before wee can <hi>attaine the reſurrection of the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But bleſt men are we, in
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:1344:71"/> that this conformitie now in a great part conſiſts one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a preparation, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to endure; when as the peace and happineſſe which wee enjoy have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd the miſery of thoſe evill dayes farre off from us, which thouſands and millions of the Saints of God have been inforced to endure. Indeed <hi>we live by faith,</hi> ſaith St. PAVL, the beſt part of our life by Faith, <hi>and not by ſight,</hi> yet what eye ſo dull, that ſees not the happineſſe of this preſent life of ours, or what tongue ſo tyed, whoſe heart will not force it to breake out into termes of gratula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>Praiſe the</hi> LORD <hi>O
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:1344:72"/> my Soule, and all that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me praiſe his holy name.</hi> Let us looke into the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times, or wee need not goe ſo farre, but on the dayes of our Fore-fathers, and how terrible then were the conditions of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? What ſtrength of grace, what a compleat ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour was then requiſite, to defend them againſt all the fiery darts of Sathan? <hi>Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtis regiae januam gradibus panarum aſcendentes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Salvian. de Guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. Dei, lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſcalas ſibi quodammodò de eculeis cataſtiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fecerunt.</hi> The wrack, the ſcourge, the ſtake, and what ever tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the witty cruelty of man was able to invent, theſe were the ſteps where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they painfully aſcended
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:1344:72"/> up to Heaven: But ſurely, if ever unto any, our <hi>yoake is eaſie, and our burthen light;</hi> in a peaceable age we reape the fruits of peace; with the freedome of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, we enjoy the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the world too; in all the faire pleaſures and delights whereof, what ever liberty a diſcreet Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then would deſire, a good Chriſtian may enjoy; and after all this, with <hi>Non obſtante</hi> to St. HIEROME,<note place="margin">Difficile imo impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibile eſt, ut quis tranſeat de deliciis in delicias. ad Iulianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Epiſt. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>de deliciis in delicias,</hi> out of the boſome of the World we may gently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move our head into ABRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HAMS boſome, quietly breath our laſt, and into the hands of our Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer commend our Spirit.
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:1344:73"/> Then indeed (to invert a little the words of St. CY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PRIAN) <hi>facta eſt Eccleſia in cruore Martyrum purpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 9.</note> the Church was of a ſcarlet dye in the blood of the Martyrs: <hi>nunc in operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus fratrum candida,</hi> now ſhe hath or may have, her garments white in the faire and peaceable converſation of the Saints. <hi>Sic florìbus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus nec lilia, nec roſae deſunt;</hi> thus hath ſhe been adorn'd and beautified with flowers of divers colours, then with the red Roſe, now the white.</p>
            <p>Yet true indeed it is, that even to this day, <hi>many are the troubles of the Righteous,</hi> but troubles common alſo with the ſinner, wherin the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:1344:73"/> graces of CHRISTS patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and humility are ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dejecting us, as that they are the chiefe comforters we have. There is a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of poverty, wherein grace cheerfully ſuſtaines us; teacheth of as well how to <hi>want,</hi> as how to <hi>abound;</hi> and if after a faire endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour wee cannot raiſe our meanes unto our minde, preſently humbles our minde unto our meanes. There is a trouble of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but yet in all our ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe grace <hi>makes all our bed. The Lord giveth</hi> (gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth health and wealth) and <hi>the Lord taketh away: and bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi> Laſtly, there is a trouble of ſinne too, which
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:1344:74"/> if grace ſhall ſometime in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, by laying the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and danger thereof neare unto our heart; yet it will eaſily perſwade us that it is good for us to bee thus troubled.</p>
            <p>For indeed ſuch is the ſtrange and powerfull effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie thereof, as that, <hi>vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus opem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>,</hi> it both woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and cureth; with a quick and ſharpe ſenſe of our ſins it oft times draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth teares from our eyes, and preſently out of a joy that it hath made us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thus ſenſible, it wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth them off againe. As then trouble is the inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable companion of our life, what more neceſſary then that grace ſhould bee
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:1344:74"/> the inſeparable companion of our trouble: that if trouble ſhould ſometime overcharge us, and force us to cry out, <hi>Wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver mee?</hi> Grace may preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuccentunate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve us, with a <hi>Thanks bee to God through</hi> IESVS CHRIST <hi>our Lord;</hi> on which firme Rocke as long as we truly faſten the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor of our hope, nor hight nor depth, nor life nor death, ſhall ever be able to remove us.</p>
            <p>Againe, are we all to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive grace for grace, grace paralell and proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the grace of CHRIST, as indeed among other cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, therfore was CHRIST
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:1344:75"/> incarnate that hee might give unto us a patterne of true grace, that in all things we may learne to be <hi>holy, as he is holy;</hi> ſurely then from hence wee may beſt put in practice that caveat of St. IOHN, and learne how to <hi>try the Spirit.</hi> By the grace of GOD (it is the common language of us all) we hope we ſhall doe well, but how ſhall we know whether the grace we ſpeake off, bee a grace in word onely, or in deed? And I hope there is no man here ſo inſenſible of ſuch things as belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his peace, but ſometime in ſecret will commune, with his owne heart, and make inquirie, <hi>Lord are there but few that ſhall bee
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:1344:75"/> ſaved,</hi> and thoſe few ſuch onely as have received the marke of thy ſpirit; how then ſhall I know whether I am partaker of this ſpirit, that I may have, if not an aſſurance, yet a faire hope that I ſhall bee of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of theſe few? A queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as very neceſſary to be made, ſo truly very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to bee reſolv'd. For mine owne part, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded there is no readier way to give our ſelves ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in this doubt, then to propoſe the doubt even in the very termes of my Text, <hi>Have I grace for grace,</hi> the grace of our Lord IESVS CHRIST, ſome commendable mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his charity, his
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:1344:76"/> zeale, his meeknes, his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, his juſtice, his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? Have I true patience and humility, true ſorrow and anguiſh of ſoule for mine owne ſinnes, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to that ſorrow of his above all ſorrowes for the ſins of the whole World? Alas otherwiſe, if we bee full of ſpleene and malice, if our mouth bee an open ſepulchre, therein ready to bury the good name and honor of every man whoſe wayes and actions doe but a little thwart us; (though yet <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel in a farre juſter conteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then can be betweene man and man, would not revile the Divell;) we know that CHRIST prayed for
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:1344:76"/> his enemies, and dyed for his enemies, and how then dwels the love of CHRIST in us? If upon every ſlight provocation we ſhall breake out into foule cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the pox, the plague, the divell, evils that we need not imprecate; happy are we if with all our prayers we can deprecate them; and theſe curſes ſhall ſecond with fearfull oaths, and at each word be prodigall of the life, the wounds, the death, the bloud, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood of <hi>Christ,</hi> one drop whereof perhaps the time may come when we ſhall call and cry for, and not bee ſo happy as to obteine it; we know that CHRIST when hee
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:1344:77"/> was reviled, reviled not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and in all our fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar diſcourſe hath confin'd us to a <hi>yea, yea,</hi> and a <hi>nay, nay;</hi> and how then dwels the meekneſſe, nay even but the language of CHRIST in us? If wee ſay unto our Soule, <hi>Take thy eaſe, eate, drinke and bee merry;</hi> and ſhall vilifie all others, who will not follow the ſame exceſſe of ryot with our ſelves: wee know that it was the ſtrict charge of CHRIST, that wee ſhould not overcharge our ſelves with ſurfetting and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſe, the baſtard parents of chambering and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, and how then dwelleth the temperance of CHRIST in us? If wee
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:1344:77"/> be alwayes querulous and diſcontent, upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> every light croſſe ready to blaſpheme the ſufferings of CHRIST, (with a <hi>non eſt dolor ſicut dolor meus) was there ever ſorrow like unto my ſorrow?</hi> wee know that CHRIST, though made a man of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, and this ſorrow for the ſinne of man, yet <hi>like the Sheepe before the Shearer hee opened not his month,</hi> and how then dwels the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of CHRIST in us? Laſtly, if wee put off the chiefe care of our Soule till the laſt houre, our prayer, our repentance, and ſtrict examination of our wayes, and thinke in the meane while that a <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> a formall devotion will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice;
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:1344:78"/> we know that CHRIST ſpent whole nights in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and in the anguiſh of his ſoule, and that for the ſenſe of our ſinnes, ſweat even drops of blood, and how then dwelleth the devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of CHRIST in us? Thoſe are quaeres able to ſtartle a good ſoule; and ſurely would we let paſſe thoſe deceivable examples, which from the frailties of men too indulgently oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we propoſe unto our ſelves, this man will doe thus, and that man thus; and ſtrive more nearly to ſquare our actions according to this infallible patterne in my Text: a world of ſinnes there are wherewith the World through cuſtome is
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:1344:78"/> now almoſt uncontroulla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly full fraught, which we ſhould then be as farre from any deſire to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, as now I feare we are from any intent to amend; and having receiv'd at firſt, though but a ſparke of grace, wee ſhould in time ſo kindle and inflame it, as that like IOHN Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, it might prove a <hi>burning and a ſhining light,</hi> by which light we might then eaſily diſcover our owne happineſſe, and ſay with IOB, <hi>Now I know that my Redeemer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſome men perhaps will heere reply, as the Patient once did to the Phyſitian, preſcribing him
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:1344:79"/> to keepe a good dyet; if I had meant, (ſaith hee) to keepe a good dyet, I ſhould never have need to come to you for Phyſicke, pray tell me how I may keepe an ill dyet and not bee ſicke: ſo you will ſay perhaps, wee al know already what good wee muſt doe, and what grace we muſt have that we may be ſaved, but pray tell us what evils we may doe, and what grace wee may want, and yet bee ſaved? May we not ſweare a little, ryot a little, and if our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved ſinne bee but little one, may not our ſoule flye thither and yet live? But firſt I pray tell mee, what ſinne is there which any man dareth cal little, which
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:1344:79"/> without repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is great, heavie, and enough to weigh him down to Hell? Indeed ſo great is the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God, as that we finde a pardon oft times given to great ſinnes; but where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver doe wee finde before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand a diſpenſation given to the leaſt? God ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time upon the fore-ſight of our repentance, antedates his pardon; <hi>Thy ſinne is forgiven thee,</hi> ſaith <hi>Nathan</hi> unto DAVID; though it is thought the ſolemne repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for this ſinne was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards perform'd: but ſhall we therefore upon the fore-intendment of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance antedate our ſin? Surely, <hi>if you would give me a houſe full of gold</hi> I dare
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:1344:80"/> not tell you ſo. For this quaere is as if a man ſhould aske, how high may I fall downe headlong, before I breake nay necke? or how often may I ſtabbe my ſelf, before I be wounded unto death? Surely becauſe a little wound oftimes proveth dangerous; or at leaſtwiſe full of paine, a wiſe man will not raſhly cut his skin; and if <hi>skin for skin, and all that a man hath hee will give for his life,</hi> how diligent and tender ought to bee every mans care for his owne ſoule? <hi>Quae inſania eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Salvian. ad Eccleſ. Cathol. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ut non quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta potes omnino facias, cum ignores penitus quid tibi com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petat ad ſalutem?</hi> What madneſſe is it for a man
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:1344:80"/> not to take the beſt care he can for his ſoule, when as he knowes that after all the care which he can take, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the <hi>Righteous ſhall ſcarce bee ſaved?</hi> Let us not then preſume to inquire, how farre we may ſuffer ſin to abound? Be we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo carefull to ſuppreſſe it, ſinne will abound too farre: but aske rather, how farre muſt grace more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, to obteyne the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of our ſinne? and when we ſee what high patternes of obedience are every where in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture propos'd unto our i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation, the perfection of the Father, the grace of the Sonne, the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Holy Ghoſt,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:1344:81"/> the Communion of Saints and Angels, may theſe great examples dayly inlarge our indeavours, and as long as wee can never hope to doe what wee ought, let us never ceaſe to doe what we may.</p>
            <p>Now then to draw all to a concluſion; We reade in this Chapter of a two fold fulneſſe in CHRIST; there is a fulneſſe of truth, and a fulneſſe of grace: fulneſſe of truth wee have reveal'd in holy Scripture, and from hence <hi>truth for truth</hi> wee are able to communicate each to others: but fulneſſe of grace this is Gods prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, which he reſerves onely to himſelfe; and <hi>grace for grace</hi> what man
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:1344:81"/> ever durſt take upon him to beſtow? Fulneſſe of truth is the religion of the ſoule, &amp; furniſheth the eye, the eare, the tongue, the head: but fulneſſe of grace, this is the ſoule of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and drawes all unto the heart: fulneſſe of truth it is a diligent MAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THA, and provideth many commendable things; but fulneſſe of grace this is the devout MARY, and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the maine neceſſary part: this is the pearle, which though wee ſhould ſell all that we have to buy, will buy a thouſand times more then wee can ſell: this is the oyle which chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the countenance, the wine which makes glad the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:1344:82"/> heart of man, and with a good conſcience keepeth a continuall feaſt. This is <hi>comes in via pro vehiculo,</hi> the moſt gentile and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full companion in the world; which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth, when honor, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrength, when wit, when ſpeech, when ſenſe, when life it ſelfe ſhall faile, will yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver leave us nor forſake us. I beſeech you then as wee cannot but all thankfully acknowledge, that we have already receiv'd the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſoule, <hi>truth for truth;</hi> let us dayly implore from Heaven the ſoule of our Religion, <hi>grace for grace;</hi> grace upon grace, even <hi>the grace of our Lord</hi> IESVS CHRIST, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:1344:82"/> given us an underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding head, hee would bee pleas'd to <hi>create in us a new heart, and renew a right ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within us:</hi> that when with the ſighes and groanes of this ſpirit, from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of this heart, we ſhall call and cry unto him <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba Father,</hi> hee may graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly make anſwer from Heaven, <hi>I will be unto thee a Father, and thou ſhalt bee to me a Sonne. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:1344:83"/>
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:1344:83"/>
            <head>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Serm. </seg>IV</label> THE FOVRTH SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLES. 12.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Remember now thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I read the ſaying of St. IOHN, <hi>My little Children this is the laſt time,</hi> the time, ſaith St. PAVL, even of the <hi>end of the world,</hi> &amp; conſider with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, that it is now neare 1600
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:1344:84"/> yeares ago, ſince this caveat was firſt given; ſurely, me thinks, wee that live at the end of this end, at the laſt period of this laſt time, have now great cauſe, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the end of the world, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> daily to bethink our ſelves of our own end, and not onely for feare of our day of death, but out of ſome reſpect alſo even unto the day of judgment; with the wife Virgins to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin betimes to prepare oyle ready for our lamps, ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly oft times to catechiſe our ſoules w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> the like que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall ſhal a yong man clenſe his wayes;</hi> and make anſwer with my Text, <hi>Remember now thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="163" facs="tcp:1344:84"/>
            <p>In the handling of which words three things I ſhall breefly commend unto you. Firſt, I will propoſe ſome reaſons and motives to perſwade the young man to be thus mindfull of his Creator: Secondly, I will remove thoſe excuſes, which all youth for the moſt part are ready to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the neglect of this duty. Laſtly, I will cloſe up all with ſome ſhort and uſefull remembrances, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> may ſerve to imprint and faſten this ſo neceſſary du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty into the meditation and practiſe of our Soules. In the handling whereof, though I have here a young man onely to remember, yet you ſhall ſee no age
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:1344:85"/> ſhall be forgotten: to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin then with the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Remember now thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the dayes of thy youth;</hi> and even for this cauſe in the dayes of thy youth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou knoweſt not whether ever thou ſhalt live till thou art old. For the life of man it is as a <hi>Shadow,</hi> and our dayes are now but a <hi>ſpanne long;</hi> nay even this ſhort mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as by ſad experience wee have too frequent tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, wee ſee ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, as that wee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy oft-times but ſome few inches even of this Spanne neither. <hi>Few and evill are the dayes of our Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage heere on earth,</hi> have
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:1344:85"/> wee now more reaſon to complaine then IACOB had. Now becauſe our dayes are <hi>evill,</hi> wee had need to remember our Creator to amend them: becauſe <hi>few,</hi> we were beſt doe it quickly; leſt we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting him, he may prove too mindfull of us, and in his juſtice cut off thoſe <hi>few</hi> dayes of ours, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee have beene ſo <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi> as not to flie unto his Mercy. And hence is it I ſhould think that St. IOHN in his firſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth ſo often ſtile the Saints of GOD by the name of <hi>little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: My little Children theſe things I write unto you; Little children keepe
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:1344:86"/> your ſelves from Idols; little children it is the laſt time:</hi> not onely to expreſſe his fatherly and tender affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over them, with whom like PAVL, hee did even <hi>goe in travaile, till</hi> CHRIST <hi>ſhould bee formed in them;</hi> not onely to teach them gentleneſſe and humility, and that hee that will enter into the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, muſt firſt ſtoop to the confeſſion of the <hi>Pſalmist, LORD I am not high min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but even as a Child wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from his Mothers breaſt, ſo doe I behave my ſelfe;</hi> but even in this reſpect al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to let us underſtand, by reaſon of the ſhortneſſe and uncertainty of the life of man, that even from our
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:1344:86"/> Childhood wee are to be trayn'd up, with the childe SAMVEL, to <hi>miniſter unto the Lord girt with a linnen Ephod,</hi> while our garments are yet <hi>white</hi> and ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, that both Body and Soule too may as it were hand in hand grow up from ſtrength to ſtrength, till of Children wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>perfect Men,</hi> and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne <hi>unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of</hi> CHRIST. For <hi>wee are all by Nature the children of wrath,</hi> all lyable to thoſe everlaſting chaynes prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the Divell and his Angels, and as long as this ſtate continueth, wee may, complaine with REBEC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CA, <hi>I am weary of my life;</hi>
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:1344:87"/> and wee may ſit downe with IOB, and curſe the <hi>day that wee were borne in:</hi> and can we then think any time too ſoone to begin to make an <hi>agreement with our adverſary by the way,</hi> by our Prayer, our repentance, our faith in the waſhing of the Bloud of IESVS, get the hand-writing of tne Law cancell'd and waſht off, that as with PAVL and SILAS in the Priſon, our fetters may fall away, and of the children of wrath we may be redeem'd into the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liberty of the ſonnes of GOD. For was it not mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in PHARAOH, when as the Frogges were now ſwarming in the Land, in his Court, in his Bedcham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:1344:87"/> in his boſome, and MOSES came kindly to him and <hi>when,</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>ſhall I intreat for thee to deſtroy theſe Frogs,</hi> was it not madneſſe (I ſay) to put him off and bid him come <hi>To morrow?</hi> Surely wee would thinke even but that one nights torture hee would have redeem'd ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though with the one halfe of his Kingdome: and are not our Sinnes as noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome companions as thoſe unwelcome gueſts of his? When then our conſcience like <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhall ſay unto our Soules, when ſhall I intreat the Lord to deſtroy theſe ſinnes, ſhould wee not be more mad then <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> did we reply, <hi>To morrow:</hi> no,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:1344:88"/> 
               <hi>To day if you will heare his voyce harden not your hearts.</hi> For the life of man as it is ſweet, ſo it is ſhort too, and though but one onely way wee have into the world, yet many out. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this or that ſhall be our end, whether ſooner or later it ſhall come, this is a ſecret which GOD hath purpoſely reſerv'd unto himſelf, that ſo wee may ever be prepared for that, from which we can never be ſecure.</p>
            <p>Let us not then put off neceſſary duties to uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine times; let us not turne Prodigals in our youth, in hope of I know not how many yeares are yet to come to cry <hi>Peccavi</hi>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:1344:88"/> in our age. For what know wee but that even in the midſt of our jollitie, when we ſhall ſay unto our ſoule <hi>Take thy eaſe and be merry;</hi> what know wee but that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then we may be arre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with a <hi>Thou foole this night ſhall thy Soule be taken from thee,</hi> and then <hi>as the Tree falls ſo it muſt lye? Quid enim ſaeculi poteſt eſſe diuturnum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. in Luc. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>cum ipſa ſaecula non ſint diuturna?</hi> For why ſhould wee preſume of our life, or any thing elſe to continue long in this world, when as the world it ſelf hath not long to continue?</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Remember now thy Creator in the dayes of thy Youth;</hi> becauſe though
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:1344:89"/> thou wert ſure to live, and wert reſolv'd to ſinne when thou art young; yet thou art not ſure to repent when thou art old, and therefore why ſhouldſt thou venture on a certaine diſeaſe upon ſo uncertaine a remedy. For the Grace of GOD it is like the Poole of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> and cureth but at ſet times, and therefore with the Cripples in the Goſpell we muſt waite all opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and call upon the name of the LORD, not when our ſelves at leyſure ſhall bee pleas'd to ſeeke after him, but when hee in his mercy will vouchſafe to be found of us. Indeed ſome Examples wee finde in holy Scripture of men,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:1344:89"/> who have made but a ſhort paſſage unto Heaven, and having not ſet forward to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward CHRIST till they came unto full yeares, have yet liv'd to overtake him, before they came unto the grave. The Thiefe, we reade it in the Goſpell, in one and the ſame day com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a malefactor to the Croſſe, and goeth a Saint to Paradiſe: but pray tell mee, for this one, this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle one, who had ſo good ſucceſſe, how many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands doe you thinke, have gone from the Croſſe to Hell? Were it not madneſs in us then to venture on that diſeaſe, whereof thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands have been caſt away upon this cold Preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:1344:90"/> that ſome odde man or two have been recovered? We are all too prone to looke on the Thiefe that hung on the right hand, but wee might doe well ſometime to think upon him who hung upon the left. For is there great Mercy with GOD, and is there not great Iuſtice too? Do but looke into the ſame Booke, and you ſhall ſee that the ſame hand hath purpoſely regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred many fearefull Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in all kinds, of men ſodainly ſurpriſed by his juſtice, even preſently up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the committing of their ſinne, that ſo the memory of theyr ends may fright us from the imitation of theyr actions, as knowing
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:1344:90"/> that what hath befallen one, may be common unto all, and that in ſuch ſinnes wherein ſome men have dyed ſo deſperately, no man can live ſecure. And ſurely as Sinnes doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves to us, would we but ſeriouſly op<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe theſe Examples unto them; and as our SAVIOUR hath already made the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to our hand, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi> LOTS <hi>wife,</hi> when having put the hand unto the plough, wee are ready to looke backe againe: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member ACHAN in our Covetouſneſſe, ABSOLON in our Diſobedience, ZIM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RI and COSBI in our Luſt, HEROD in our Pride, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NANIAS in our Hypocriſie
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:1344:91"/> and the like; ſurely I ſay, would we but ſeriouſly lay theſe precedents to heart, the feare of the puniſhment would ſoon fright us from the love of the ſinne. Let us not then preſuming on GODS patience provoke his anger; Let us not fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwade our ſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no time is too late for him to forgive, that therefore any time is ſoone enough for us to repent: no, if wee will be ſure to ſing a <hi>requiem</hi> at our going out of the world, let us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin our <hi>miſerere</hi> at our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in.<note place="margin">Ambroſ. de Paenit. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Infir maſpes quae com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur tempori, cum omne tempus incertum ſit, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ſpes tempori ſuperſtes;</hi> for weak is our preſent truſt or
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:1344:91"/> time to come, when as we know that all time to come is uncertaine. Nor can we certainly truſt all time that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, becauſe that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of GOD w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed pardon wherever we ſhall repent, hath no where promiſed repentance when ever our ſelves pleaſe.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Remember now thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth, becauſe in the dayes of thy youth thy Creator hath remembred thee: who is it from whom thou haſt receiv'd thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? Are not <hi>children, &amp; the fruit of the womb a guift that commeth of the Lord?</hi> who is it by whom thou liveſt, and moveſt, and enjoyeſt the bleſſings of this life? doe
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:1344:92"/> not <hi>the eyes of all things waite upon thee O Lord, and thou filleſt every living thing with Plenteouſneſſe?</hi> Who is it that amidſt all the caſualties of the world preſerveth thee in thy go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out and in thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in? Hath not he <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his Angels charge ever thee, that thou ſhalt not ſo much as daſh thy foot against a ſtone?</hi> So that from thy firſt conception to this houre, one day telling ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what great things he that is mighty hath done for thee; what canſt thou doe leſſe in teſtimonie of thy thankfulneſſe then to ſerve him without feare in holineſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe all the dayes of thy
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:1344:92"/> life? GODS remembrance of thee, it is voluntary, but thine of him is of neceſſity. Hee can ſay of the beſt of men, I have no need of you, but can the beſt man ſay to him, I have no need of thee? If then his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe freely moove him to be mindfull of thee, let thy duty conſtraine thee to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him. And that not without juſt cauſe; for unleſſe thou ſhalt put him in mind to perfect the worke of his owne hands, and to his creation of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture adde the creation of Grace alſo, a thouſand times better had it beene that thou hadſt been quite forgotten, and not Created at all. For however of all
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:1344:93"/> the Creatures of the earth man be the moſt noble and divine; yet ſimply to be a man is but a doubtfull bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, thou knoweſt not yet whether thou ſhalt be lov'd or hated. That which puts all out of doubt muſt be a new creation; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if thou deſire to take up the language of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee but with a better minde, <hi>Lord I thanke thee that I am not as other men are,</hi> now no more an olde but a new creature; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy Creator with the prayer of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Create in me O Lord a cleane heart, and renew a right ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within me,</hi> a ſpirit wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our hearts may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged with obedience and
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:1344:93"/> thankfulneſſe, and dayly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of our duties unto him, according to the largeneſſe of his goodneſſe and mercy, and continuall mindfulneſſe of us, and then <hi>Quàm beati eſſemus, ſi quàm promptam erga nos Dei audientiam legimus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Salvian. de Gubernat. Dei. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>taem prompto ipſum audire veli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> O how happy ſhould wee be, were we but halfe ſo ready to heare and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the commands of GOD, as we are to overheare and challenge his promiſes. And thus much for the reaſons and motives to perſwade the young man to remember his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. I come now in the ſecond place to anſwer his objections.</p>
            <pb n="182" facs="tcp:1344:94"/>
            <p>Firſt then it may bee urg'd, muſt the young man ſo early begin to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his Creator? Muſt the tender neck preſently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſubject to this heavie yoake, no ſooner have we with-drawne our hand from the <hi>ferula,</hi> and come newly but to feele and know our ſelves, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently muſt wee be bound in a perpetuall apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and that to a harder Maſter then before? This is a hard ſaying, and who is able to endure it, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly would wee take up our croſſe and follow CHRIST, but gladly would wee have a little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite firſt, to go and bid the world farewell.</p>
            <pb n="183" facs="tcp:1344:94"/>
            <p>Indeed were Religion an eaſie profeſſion, it might more eaſily bee deferr'd: Things wherein there is leſſe difficulty, require leſſe induſtry: But becauſe all the World will grant that it is very hard to bee good, ſurely wee had need to begin betimes. Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie then you ſee which is urg'd as an objection to put off Religion till olde age, proves a ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to perſwade us to be religious in our youth: yet notwithſtanding could it but well appeare, that the ſame yoake, which puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us in our youth, would prove more eaſie to old age the excuſe might bee more pardonable: But for my
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:1344:95"/> part when I conſider that all Trades, all Arts, all Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, are in their firſt ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments, beſt learnt in our minority; I cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded but that religion alſo, (which with pretence of difficulty, becauſe wee are unwilling to make triall of our owne ſtrength, wee are all too ready to put off till wee are old) will yet prove moſt facile in our youth: And hee that ſhall compare the ſeverall advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages which age and youth have each of other in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, will finde perhaps that it is no para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox to maintain againſt the great Philoſopher, that <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenis eſt magis idoneus audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor moralis and divinae Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophiae
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:1344:95"/> too,</hi> that a young <hi>Timothy</hi> is a fitter Auditor of a lecture of Divinity, than an old <hi>Nicodemus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Age I confeſſe, to give it its due honour, hath many prerogatives of youth. Age is coole and temperate; thoſe hot purſuites of vain delights if grace reſtraine not, wee ſee in time nature itſelfe forbeares. Age it is ſtayed and reſolute; good courſes well begun it will hold on: though the hand bee hardly drawne unto the plough, yet the eye will not ſuddainely looke backe againe. Age it is wiſe and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc't, and having made frequent triall of the fickle unconſtancie of all things
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:1344:96"/> under the Sunne, can now truely ſay of laughter, <hi>Thou art madneſse,</hi> and that all the glory of the world, it is <hi>but vanity and vexation of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> Laſtly, Age it is ſickly and craz'd, and daily draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth onward nearer to the grave; &amp; we ſee the tongue no not of men and Angels to be ſo powerfull an Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to proclaime unto us. <hi>Duſt thou art, and to duſt thou muſt returne,</hi> as but one dumbe fit of a diſeaſe. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEXANDER whom in his health all the World could not perſwade but that a GOD hee would needs be, upon a wound receiv'd ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the blood come, could then humble his conceit, <hi>&amp; jam ſentio me mortalem,</hi>
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:1344:96"/> and now I ſee, ſaith he, that I muſt dye: ſo that the old man dayly ſeeing that death, which may be neare unto the young man, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be far off from him, is the more eaſily perſwaded to prepare himſelfe for the more eaſie paſſage when it comes. Theſe indeed are great advantages of age, and yet perhaps the young man hath farre greater.</p>
            <p>For firſt, Youth it is baſhfull and modeſt: and modeſty, (ſaith the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher) if it be not a vertue, it is vertues companion. And thus much Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie alſo ſeemes to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, when wee ſay of a man that is not yet paſt ſhame, that ſurely he is not
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:1344:97"/> yet paſt Grace. For ſhame oft-times it is the Guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an of Grace, and many ſins there are for the forbeara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wherof even the beſt Soules are ſometime as much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to their modeſty, as to their Religion But age you know it is more bold and daring, and therefore oft-times for want of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues companion, vertue her ſelfe proves wanting, and the loſſe of ſhame becomes the ruine of Grace. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, Youth it is alwayes ſubject to controll, hath a Father, a Mother, a Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, a Maſter, or if all theſe may fayle, yet old age it ſelfe, wee ſee, if for no other cauſe, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe old, it challengeth
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:1344:97"/> a kind of Fatherhood o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all youth, and if but old ELIES gentle reproofe, <hi>Nay my Sonnes why doe you ſuch things,</hi> it leaves ſome impreſſion in the Soule. But age 'tis uncontrolable, <hi>Rebuke not an Elder,</hi> it is the precept in the Text, and ELIHU in IOB converſing with his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, though they gave him juſt cauſe of ſpeech and reproofe too, yet you ſee how long hee layes his hand upon his mouth before ever hee durſt ſpeake: ſo that wee ſee oft-times the greater is the old mans libertie, the greater alſo is his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. Againe, youth it is more free and generous; in
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:1344:98"/> all dealings of the world li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth neareſt to the beſt law of nature, <hi>Do as thou wouldſt be done unto,</hi> not ſo ready to defraud, and yet more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to reſtore. But Age, it is penurious and griping, and now come in thoſe cruell times of extortion and oppreſſion, <hi>Quocumque modo rem,</hi> a man will <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe even for a peece of bread.</hi> Laſtly, and that which is the maine advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, youth it is like golde, ſoft and pliable, if ſoone bent, ſoone ſet to rights a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; but age, it is like I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, ſullen and ſtiffe: Youth indeed it is more heady, but tendermouth'd; but age it is more headſtrong, if it flie out, it will run its courſe;
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:1344:98"/> the old mans Motto is like that of PILATE, <hi>Quod ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi ſcripſi,</hi> Hee will have his will. Sinnes of youth they are but ill diſpoſitions; but ſinnes of age they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ill habits. Here the fleſh turneth Traitor, and rebelleth againſt the Spirit; but there it turneth Tyrant and commandeth. In the dayes of our youth, GOD patiently ſtandeth at the doore of our hearts and knocketh; and when hee hath ſpoke once and twice, though wee regard not, hee will not yet preſently leave us nor forſake us: but when once thirty or forty yeares long he hath beene grieved with a rebellious and gaine-ſaying
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:1344:99"/> generation, in the end his patience turneth to anger, <hi>What could I have done which I have not done?</hi> and ſo gives them over to a reprobate ſence.</p>
            <p>Thus then you ſee the young man alſo hath his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, and indeed what ever precedence our age can chalenge of our youth, it is then onely to be found when the old man ploughes with the young mans heckfer: For then it is no wonder, that the incomes of our age multiplying up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtocke of our youth ſhould make the fairer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venew: but ſet the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon right, and then thus much I dare boldlie
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:1344:99"/> ſay, that whereas in theſe dayes of ours, whereof out of zeale I preſume to make them better, wee wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully complaine oft-times as if they never had beene worſe; many rare and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous young men are not perhaps ſo rare to bee found: yet I thinke it is almoſt a miracle to ſee a very good old man, who never began to bee good till hee was old. If then vertue be ſo hard a taske, as to excuſe our vices wee are all too eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie perſwaded to beleeve; ſurely in all diſcretion wee are to make choyce of the fitteſt ſeaſon to attaine it, and that I have ſhewen you are the daies of our Youth.
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:1344:100"/> For let ſinne have but its courſe a while, and if you will not beleeve me; Saint AVGUSTINE ſhall tell you what will be the iſſue. <hi>Ex voluntate perverſa facta eſt libido,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Confeſſ. lib <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; dum ſervitur libi dini, facta eſt conſuetudo, &amp; dum conſuetudini non reſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, factu eſt neceſſitas.</hi> From a perverſe will, which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally wee all bring into the World, ariſe ſinfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and while we humor our deſire, cuſtome layes hold upon us, and while this cuſtome is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trold it proves another na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Heere then you ſee the difficulties of Sinne: they are like the waters mentioned by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, begin at the ankles,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:1344:100"/> riſe to the knees, thence to the waſte, after to the neck, till in the end they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme us. Were it not better then at the firſt to venture over ſhooes, then at the laſt over head and eares? and therefore while the waters are yet low and paſſable, before the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowings of ungodlineſſe ſhall too much fright our ſoules, let mee commend unto you that Item of our SAVIOUR but upon a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter errand, <hi>Quod facis fac cito?</hi> That which thou meaneſt to doe, doe quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And thus much for the firſt objection, I come now to anſwer a ſecond.</p>
            <pb n="196" facs="tcp:1344:101"/>
            <p>For Religion you will ſay, and the early remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thoſe duties which we owe to our Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator they breed melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and fright the Soule with many ſad and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate thoughts; not an idle word can be ſpoken, not a <hi>Racha</hi> given or <hi>Thou foole,</hi> not the leaſt riot or exceſſe committed, but preſently the conſcience checks us with judgment and Hell fire; and gladly would we deſire the freedom to live a little chearly in our youth.</p>
            <p>Thus have I ſeene a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ſometime complaine of his Phyſick, when as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he was heart ſicke of his diſeaſe. For pray, tell me what is it, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> in thoſe
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:1344:101"/> ſad fits, whereto the Soules of good men are oft-times ſubject, (and perhaps did we more often feele them the more happy might we be;) what is it I ſay, which breeds this melancholy, is it our Religion? that wee know is the Phyſicke of the Soule: no ſurely, it is our ſin, and that is the diſeaſe. Were it not madneſſe in us then, to deſire to live freely in our ſinne, that we might live free from ſorrow, when as indeed there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing truly to be ſorrowed for but ſinne? For let us reckon up a catalogue of all ſuch delights, as our owne Soule would wiſh to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre to make a cheerefull life, and you ſhall ſee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:1344:102"/> hath the promiſe of them all. <hi>Wouldſt thou injoy long life, and ſee good dayes? Keepe thy tongue from vill, and thy lippes that they ſpeake no guile.</hi> And this life of thine wouldſt thou have as healthfull as 'tis long? <hi>Praiſe the Lord O my Soule, for he it is that reneweth thy ſtrength, and maketh thee young and luſty as an Eagle.</hi> And this health of thine wouldſt thou have main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with plenty, <hi>Truſt in the Lord and doe good, and verily thou ſhalt be fed, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the Lord and hee ſhall give thee thy hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</hi> And this plenty of thine, wouldſt thou have ſeconded with joy? <hi>O be joyfull in the Lord all yee
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:1344:102"/> Lands; ſerve the Lord with gladneſſe, and come before his preſence with a ſong.</hi> And laſtly, of this joy of thine, wouldſt thou have a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, not for thy ſelfe one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but for thy poſterity? <hi>The Righteous ſhall dwell at eaſe, and his ſeed ſhall inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the Land.</hi> If then life and health, plenty and joy, can make a cheerefull man, certainly religion cannot make him melancholly. But yet I muſt confeſſe theſe rare effects, they are perhaps but rarely to bee found, and ſhort life, craz'd health, ſmall plenty, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant joyes they are the portion oft-times even of GODS deareſt Saints; not that GOD hath forgotten to
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:1344:103"/> bee ſo good as his word promiſeth, but that men have not remembred to be ſo good as his word com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth, but have neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the performance of thoſe ſtrict conditions, whereupon the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of theſe ſo large promiſes depend. But however do the righteous, and ſuch as daylie remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their Creator, doe they onely eate ſowre Grapes, and are the ſinners ſuch as have not GOD in all theyr thoughts, are their teeth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſet on edge? It is true indeed, that <hi>GOD receives no man but whom hee doth chaſtice,</hi> chaſtice not with croſſe and affliction one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but with ſorrow and
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:1344:103"/> anguiſh of Soule, with feare and trembling for his ſin; yet here wee have a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of little judgement with great mercy, the ioy of our receiving ſoone eaſing the ſmart of our chaſticement. But is it not true withall, that the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner hee ſhall receive his chaſticement and yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bee received; here is iudgement without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. With the righteous heavineſſe may endure for a night, but ioy commeth in the morning: but with the ſinner this order is inverted; ioy indeed may endure for a night, but ſorrow returnes in the Morning. When up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſober view of
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:1344:104"/> of his intemperate luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances finding his Soule like CAINS, guilty of more ſinne then he knoweth how to have forgiven, hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſubject to the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full expectation of more pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhment, then hee knowes which way to endure.</p>
            <p>Indeed if we looke upon the ſurface of things onely, the ſinner may ſeeme to be the onely chearly man, ſits downe merrily to eate and drinke, riſeth to his play, and wondereth that any man ſhould refuſe to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſame exceſſe of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot with himſelfe. But let us now a little change his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and remove him from his owne table, which from the exceſſe and riot
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:1344:104"/> thereof I feare we may too juſtly ofttimes ſtile the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Devils, and bring him to the Table of the Lord, and then behold with how heavie a heart doth he reach forth his trembling hand to pertake of thoſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred myſteries, as juſtly fearing upon this Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his great unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, leſt he ſhould eate and drinke his own condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and riſe up ſeavenfold more the child of Hell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſate downe. When as the Righteous commeth with joy &amp; chearfulneſſe, whoſe innocent conſcience as it keepeth a continuall feaſt, ſo never then now is it more plentifully fed, and thankfully (ſaith Grace)
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:1344:105"/> with a <hi>Nunc dimittis, Lord now letteſt thou thy Servant depart in peace: for mine eyes have ſeene my Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> For now I know that the <hi>Kingdome of Heaven,</hi> (true happineſſe indeed) <hi>it is not meate and drinke, but Righteouſneſſe, and peace, and joy upon joy, joy unſpeakable, even joy in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> It is a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſpeech of HAMAN, who recounting the glory of his riches, the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his children, the great honours whereunto hee had beene promoted above other Princes by the King; yet in the end concludeth, <hi>All this is nothing, as long as</hi> MOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DECAL <hi>ſits in the Kings
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:1344:105"/> gate.</hi> So ſurely hee that ſhall examine the Soules of the <hi>Hamans</hi> of this World, men who for pleaſure, wealth, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſeeme to be the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happy men; will finde them ſometime ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to confeſſe, <hi>All this is nothing:</hi> for there is a MORDECAI, a tormenting conſcience, dayly ſitting in the Gate, which like IONAS his Worme, no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is the Gourd of their felicitie ſprung up a little, but preſently it biteth and gnaweth it downe againe. And therefore we ſee daily nothing more frequent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the luxurious prodigall upon the ſad remembrance of the follies of his youth,
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:1344:106"/> to breake out <hi>into a Lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare ſterilis,</hi> Happie are the barren, and the Soules unſenſible of theſe vaine delights, the fruition whereof is but a tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vanity, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance a perpetuall vexation of the Spirit. As then GOD ſaid once un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Iewes, Bring my tithes into my ſtore-houſe, and prove mee now if I will not open the windors of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and powre downe a bleſſing without meaſure;</hi> ſo let me ſay here to young and old, Remember now thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth, in the dayes of thy age, even all the dayes of thy life, ſerve him in chaſtity, in temperance,
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:1344:106"/> in juſtice, in charitie, in prayer, in repentance; make a tryall of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſee whether he will not open the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of Heaven, and in ſtead of ſadneſſe and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly, powre downe joy and gladneſſe, the joy and comforts of his Grace and Spirit, whereby like the wiſe men at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the Starre, thou ſhalt daylie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce and that exceeding greatly.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe it were true that the ſinner had the whole world at will, came into no miſfortune like other men, were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to no diſcontent, no ſorrow; yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:1344:107"/> mee thinks, that one ſaying of <hi>Lactantius</hi> might ſerve to ſettle and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the affections of a good man in the conſtant profeſſion of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, againſt all the feares and melancholies which for conſcience and Religions ſake hee might be ſubject to.<note place="margin">Inſtitut. lib. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bonis brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus mala aeterna, &amp; malis brevibus bona aeterna, &amp;c.</hi> So hath the providence of GOD ordeined, that for ſhort pleaſures hee hath threatned us with eternall paines, for ſhort paines hee hath made promiſe of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall pleaſures. Let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man therefore ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie conſider with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, how much better
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:1344:107"/> it is to be ſubject here un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a little ſorrow, an aſſurance hereafter of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall joy, then for ſhort and tranſitorie joyes to expoſe himſelfe unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſorrow. And thus much by way of anſwer to the young mans Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections; I come now in the laſt place to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend unto him a few ſhort and uſefull Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrances, and then I conclude.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Remember now thy Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator in the dayes of thy Youth:</hi> Remember from the dayes of thy Youth, even from thy infancie, to whoſe ſervice thou haſt ſo ſolemnly been conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, what promiſes, what
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:1344:108"/> vowes have beene made, at the partaking of one Baptiſme, to embrace one Faith, to ſerve one Lord; and be not deceived, GOD <hi>will not be mockt,</hi> thou art not now thine owne man, thou haſt not the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to goe ſerve ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Maſter.<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Ioh. Tract. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Deus non vult communionem, ſed ſolus vult poſſidere quod emit.</hi> For GOD cannot endure a Partner, but what hee hath purchaſt alone, hee will poſſeſſe alone. <hi>Tanti enim emit, ut ſolus poſſideat,</hi> and indeed ſo deare a price hath hee payed for thy ſoule, that well may he challenge the whole purchaſe to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <pb n="211" facs="tcp:1344:108"/>
            <p>Remember the way to Heaven is difficult, and at each third ſtep there are mazes and by-paths, and therefore be not raſh in thy courſe, but ſtand oft times and make a pauſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire which is the old and the right way. Will theſe actions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> theſe thoughts, this company, this diſcourſe, this idleneſſe, this expence, will theſe lead a man to Heaven? And though thou often ſee good men take an oblique courſe like the Sunne, croſſe the line and backe againe,<note place="margin">Hieron. Epiſt. <hi>9.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> edit. Caniſ.</note> yet alwayes remember, <hi>Securiùs eſſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rire non poſſe, quam juxta pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculum non periſſe;</hi> that it is the ſafer way not to have ventur'd on a danger, then
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:1344:109"/> to have eſcap't it.</p>
            <p>Remember alwayes in the ſerious eſtimation of thy ſinne, not to follow the looſe account of men, who are ready to ſet downe fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for an hundred, nay ſometime ſcarce one of a thouſand, but the true and juſt account of God. Call no ſinne light, which with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out repentance is heavie enough to weigh thee downe to Hell. Think not ſo much on the ſmalneſſe of the command, as the greatneſſe of the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. For even ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands oft times, as we ſee by the example of the fall of ADAM, <hi>tanto majori ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tia violantur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug Civ Dei, l. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quanto fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliori obſervantia poterant
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:1344:109"/> cuſtodivi,</hi> are with ſo much the greater injuſtice viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the greater juſtice pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, by how much with the eaſier obſervance they might have beene fulfilled.</p>
            <p>Remember alwayes to prize thy ſoule not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy nature but thy grace. The guifts of nature, gentleneſſe, civility, wit, underſtanding, memory, may raiſe us oft times like <hi>Saul</hi> higher then the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and get their applauſe who judge onely by appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but they are the guifts of grace, which like DAVID muſt make us gracious with God, and winne his heart. <hi>Melius eſt eſſe digitum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Iohan. Tract. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; eſſe in corpore, quam eſſe
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:1344:110"/> oculum &amp; evelli de corpore.</hi> For a thouſand times bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is in the eye of God to ſtand though but for a finger, and be joyn'd unto the body; then in the eye of man to looke like an eye, and yet to bee pluckt out.</p>
            <p>Remember alwayes to part thy care between thy body and thy ſoule, and if ſo much time bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps too pleaſingly ſpent in the food, the dreſſe, the ſleepe, the recreation of the one; doe not forget to ſet apart ſome time alſo for the other.<note place="margin">Bernard Sermon <hi>6.</hi> de Advent. dom.</note> 
               <hi>Noli O corpus, noli praecipere tempora.</hi> For why ſhould the pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering of the body ſteale away that time, which
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:1344:110"/> might be farre better ſpent in the tending of the ſoule. <hi>Potes enim impedire animae tuae ſalutem, tuam ipſius ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari non potes,</hi> too much care of the body, may ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine it ſelfe and the ſoule too; but it is the ſoule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, which muſt ſave both ſoule and body.</p>
            <p>Laſtly and to conclude all; Remember that at the will of the Lord, thou art but a Copy-holder of thine owne life; the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of thy body, at his pleaſure he hath ſet up, and at the ſame pleaſure he will pluck downe againe; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the firſt or the laſt watch, whether in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or evening of thy dayes thou canſt not tell:
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:1344:111"/> and therefore watch al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, that thou mayſt be prepared, that when ever thou ſhalt lay downe this earthly Tabernacle of thy body, thou maiſt with joy and cheerfulneſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend thy ſoule into the hands of thy Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, in hope of an Eternall Manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Heavens. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="sermon">
            <pb n="217" facs="tcp:1344:111"/>
            <head>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Serm. </seg>V</label> THE FIFTH SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IOHN 20.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Touch mee not, for I am not yet aſcended to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time was come, God ſent forth his Sonne made of a woman;</hi> that as in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:1344:112"/> 
               <hi>the woman</hi> (ſaith St. PAVL) <hi>was in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion;</hi> firſt in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, <hi>not the man;</hi> ſo now the ſeed of the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not the ſeed of the man, was to obteine pardon for this tranſgreſſion, reconcile the woman to the man, and both to God. And ſurely it is not without a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, in the performance of this great myſterie of our redemption, by the paſſion and reſurrection of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; that when the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard was now ſmitten, and the Sheep (the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) the men were ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yet the women they hold faſt together: <hi>his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mothers ſiſter,</hi> MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY MAGDALEN, and MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:1344:112"/> 
               <hi>of Cleophas,</hi> with many others, ſtand reſolute by the Croſſe. The firſt that after his buriall durſt come unto his ſepulchre were women, and that for the greater commendation of this fearfull Sex, <hi>early in the morning, while it was yet darke.</hi> The firſt to whom the Reſurrection was made knowne were women, <hi>Why ſeeke ye the living among the dead</hi> (ſaith the Angell to theſe women) <hi>He is riſen, he is not heere.</hi> The firſt to whom our SAVIOVR him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe appeared, was a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; <hi>Woman why weepeſt thou?</hi> ſaith he to MARY MAGDALEN. Laſtly, the firſt that had the honour to carry theſe glad tydings to
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:1344:113"/> his Diſciples was a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; <hi>Goe to my Brethren</hi> (ſaith he to the ſame MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY) <hi>and ſay unto them I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend unto my Father.</hi> But a little before PETER and IOHN were there, they went both into the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre; yet they ſee, they heare nothing; why did not our Saviour ſhew himſelfe to them, but MARY muſt be his Meſſenger? CHRY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SOLOGVS wil give you the true reaſon; <hi>Vt portet vitae, portet reſurrectionis auditum, quae auditum mortis portave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat &amp; ruina;</hi> That as the woman had beene the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy agent betweene the the divell and man to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his fall; ſo now the woman might have the
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:1344:113"/> happineſſe to be imployed betweene God and man, and recommend and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deere her ſelfe again by the joyfull news of his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. If then ſo great hath beene the honour vouchſafed unto this Sexe, and above al unto this MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY, how comes it to paſſe, that amidſt ſo many cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies, we find here ſo great a ſtrangeneſſe in my Text? Shee that firſt ſees him, ſpeaketh to him, goeth on his errand, muſt not (it ſeemes) preſume to touch him, <hi>Touch mee not, for I am not yet aſcended to my Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words, great is the difficultie if wee ſhall enquire, eyther why our
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:1344:114"/> Saviour ſhould thus prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite MARY to touch him, <hi>Touch me not;</hi> or why hee ſhould give this reaſon for his prohibition; <hi>for I am not yet aſcended to may Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> In the handling of which words, firſt I will indeavour to cleare the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties thereof, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly in ſeverall obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, apply all unto our ſelves.</p>
            <p>To begin then with the difficulty of this ſtrange prohibition, <hi>Touch me not;</hi> Wherein ſhall we ſay with ſome that CHRIST being riſen from the dead, his mortall having put on im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie, and death being ſwallowed up in victory, begins now to keepe a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:1344:114"/> requires a more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent reſpect, wil not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcend to the like familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which he had ſuffered heretofore; and therefore ſeemeth heere to give a check to MARY, comming after her wonted manner to embrace him, <hi>Touch me not?</hi> But ſurely this cannot be the reaſon, for we read in the laſt of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> that this ſame woman with many others, and in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability even at this ſame time, did touch him, touch him without controll, <hi>hold him by the feet, and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped him:</hi> and appearing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward to his Diſciples, he was ſo farre from beeing thus eſtrang'd, as that, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>my hands and
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:1344:115"/> my feet;</hi> touch me, nay more, <hi>handle mee,</hi> touch mee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and againe: and St. IOHN in his firſt Epiſtle bringeth this as an evidence of his Reſurrection. <hi>That which wee have heard,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that which we have ſeen,</hi> nay more, <hi>that which our hands have handled of the word of life, declare we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</hi> Or ſhall wee ſay with others, that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our doth not in theſe words reprehend MARY, but inform her: ſhe thought perhaps that CHRIST be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing riſen from the dead; would preſently aſcend unto the Father; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now with one large ſalutation ſhee bids him welcome from the dead,
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:1344:115"/> ſhee taketh her farewell from among the living, ſhee falleth downe, ſhee holdeth him by the feet, ſhee worſhippeth him, and thinketh ſhee cannot now touch him too long, as beeing never to touch him any more? And for this cauſe they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our Saviour might heere ſay, <hi>Touch mee not,</hi> that is; Doe not embrace mee now, as if you were to take your laſt fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well; for I am not yet aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending to my Father, have many dayes to continue here on earth, and you ſhall have time enough hereafter to viſite, to embrace, to diſcourſe, and therfore now forbeare
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:1344:116"/> your ſalutations, ariſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and make others par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with your ſelfe of the ſame joy, <hi>Goe tell my Brethren, that I aſcend unto my Father.</hi> But this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, however at the firſt propoſall ſomewhat plauſible, yet in the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation will not hold. For firſt it ſeemeth more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, as I ſhall ſhew you anon, that MARY was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken rather in thinking that hee would ſtay longer then himſelfe intended, then that hee would goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſooner then her ſelfe deſir'd. And ſeondly we doe not read that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our did ever afterward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to MARY, nay it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth rather by the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:1344:116"/> ſhe was to deliver, <hi>I aſcend unto my Father,</hi> that he would informe her that he was not to ſtay long, and that hee meant not to be ſeen often. We may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in the laſt of St. IOHN, <hi>This is now the third time,</hi> but the third time onely, <hi>that</hi> CHRIST <hi>ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to his Diſciples;</hi> and if but thrice to them, ſurely not ſo often to MARY, that for this cauſe hee ſhould diſmiſſe her now, as if there would bee time enough hereafter, <hi>Touch me not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely then ſome other cauſe muſt bee found out, for the full diſcovery whereof, two things I ſhall obſerve. Firſt that MARY is not heere ſimply forbid
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:1344:117"/> to touch her Maſter, that is, to ſalute and to embrace him: for St. <hi>Matth.</hi> plainly tells us, that not MARY on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but all the women <hi>held him by the feet and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped him:</hi> and this embracing of the feet it was a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolemne ſalutation among the Iewes. Thus the <hi>Shuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite</hi> takes ELISHA by the feet, <hi>Abigail</hi> falls at the feet of DAVID, the Ruler of the Synagogue, the woman of <hi>Cannaan,</hi> at the feet of IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS; <hi>Cornelius</hi> at the feet of PETER, IOHN of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell: onely ſhee is advis'd here not to be too long, too paſſionate in her ſalutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For it may ſeem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that when all the other women were riſen from
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:1344:117"/> the ground, ſtill <hi>Mary</hi> knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, imbraceth him, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth him by the feet, and as ſhe loved much, ſtriveth by her very geſture to teſtifie the greatneſſe of her love. And we know there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more uſuall in holy ſcripture, then in the ſame latitude of terms to forbid the exceſſe of actions, as if the actions themſelves were forbidden: <hi>I will have mercy and not ſacrifice;</hi> that is not ſacrifice in compariſon of mercy: <hi>Labour not for the meat that periſeth, Take no thought for tomorrow;</hi> that is no labor, no thought, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the thought and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor for that meat w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures to everlaſting life; ſo here, <hi>Touch me not;</hi> that is,
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:1344:118"/> doe not too long lye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate at my feet, doe not dwell upon your ſalutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; or, as wee uſe to ſay; Doe not hang upon mee. Secondly, that ſuch was the ignorance not of MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY onely, but of all the Diſciples in this great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of CHRISTS riſing from the dead, as that till the day of his Aſcenſion they were ſtill ſtrongly poſſeſt with the conceipt of ſome great worldly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, which ſhould now preſently befall them. All thoſe Spirituall diſcourſes concerning the <hi>Kingdome of Heaven, the twelve Thrones, the Houſes and Lands,</hi> they apprehend in a carnall ſenſe: and hence
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:1344:118"/> is it that they ſo often quarrell <hi>who ſhould be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt in the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> And what was their earthly conceit of this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Kingdome, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by that queſtion of theirs in the firſt of the <hi>Acts: Lord wilt thou not now reſtore the Kingdome,</hi> (or the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) <hi>unto Iſrael?</hi> meaning thereby ſuch a felicitie in this life, whereby they hop't to enjoy a little hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon earth: and this ſeemeth to bee one maine reaſon of MARIES ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive joyes and ſalutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; now at length ſhee hop'd the Kingdome would bee reſtored, the Thrones erected, the
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:1344:119"/> Houſes and Lands divided, upon the falſe apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of which imaginarie happineſſe, our SAVIOVR thus gently correcteth and informeth her, <hi>Touch mee not.</hi> Be not therefore over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd with my preſence, doe not for this cauſe ſo zealouſly imbrace mee, as if I were now riſen to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the Kingdome unto <hi>Iſrael:</hi> for <hi>my Kingdome,</hi> I have told you, <hi>is not of this world;</hi> but as I am now riſen from the grave, ſo muſt I ſhortly aſcend from the earth too, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to Heaven unto my Father; and there is the place of your true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, there are the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which I am going to
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:1344:119"/> prepare, and therefore now ariſe, and that my brethren may not deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the like world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expectations; <hi>Goe tell them that I aſcend unto my Father.</hi> And indeed very remarkable it is, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever our Saviour, after his riſing from the dead, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſtay forty dayes, before his aſcenſion up to Heaven, to certifie and publiſh the truth of his Reſurrection, to recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the diſtracted thoughts of his Diſciples; yet in all his apparitions hee diſcovereth himſelfe ſtrangely, and by ſtarts, in one forme to MARY, in another to the two Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth ſodainly to
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:1344:120"/> their aſtoniſhment while the doores are ſhut, and after ſome ſhort confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence leaveth them as much amaz'd, and vaniſheth out of their ſight: and heere you ſee MARY hath ſcarce leaſure to bid him wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, but preſently he is ready to bid her farewell. And all this was done, that by thus ſtrangely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing it might manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare, that therefore he declin'd the frequence and concourſe of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, therefore he refrain'd the reiterating of his plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible miracles, therefore he withdrew himſelfe from the familiarity even of his owne brethren, that hee might draw their mindes
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:1344:120"/> from that ſtrong intention wherewith they were fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened on things earthly, that he might let them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that hee was not now riſen to reſtore the Kingdome unto <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and then afterwards, as they perhaps might ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, dye againe; but that, as St. PAVL ſaith, <hi>beeing raiſed from the dead hee might dye no more, death might have no more domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over him: for in that he dyed, he dyed unto ſinne once, but that he liveth he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth unto God;</hi> liveth not to continue upon earth, but to aſcend to Heaven unto his Father, and therefore now, <hi>Touch me not,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Set not your affections on
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:1344:121"/> things below, but ſeeke thoſe things which are above.</hi> And thus much for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of my Text; I come now to commend ſome obſervations to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Firſt then when we ſee, after ſo many heavenly inſtructions, the earthly-mindedneſſe of <hi>Mary,</hi> that ſo are her thoughts fixt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on things below, and for this cauſe ſo is ſhee over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd with the preſence of her Maſter, as that hee is forc'd with a gentle checke to reprove her indiſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Touch mee not.</hi> This may teach us as St. IOHN hath already made the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to our hand, <hi>that we love not,</hi> love not too
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:1344:121"/> well, <hi>the world, nor the things of the world,</hi> that in our prayers and deſires we bee not too ſolicitous; Would I had this Houſe, this Land, this Wealth, this Honour, leſt beeing guilty of the ſame errour, wee may bee ſubject to the ſame cenſure, and ſeeme to heare from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, a <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> doe not for this cauſe <hi>Touch me,</hi> doe not importune mee. It is a memorable an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of our SAVIOVR, when the Mother made that ambitious requeſt, <hi>Grant that my two Sonnes may ſit, one at thy right hand, and another at thy left hand in thy Kingdome; Are you able,</hi> ſaith he,
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:1344:122"/> 
               <hi>to drinke of the Cup, that I ſhall drinke of, and to bee baptized with the baptiſme, that I ſhall be baptized with?</hi> not with the baptiſme of water and the ſpirit, but with blood and Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: the more pleaſing and honourable are the conditions ſhe deſireth, the more harſh and unpleaſant are the conditions he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth; as indeed there is nothing more frequent with God, then to anſwer the deſires of men by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries, becauſe they are contrary oft times to that main end, which we ſhould all deſire; the good and welfare of our ſoules. And thogh we al know, <hi>Not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny noble, not many rich,</hi> but
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:1344:122"/> 
               <hi>Bleſſed rather are the poore, bleſſed are you when you ſuffer perſecution;</hi> yet we are all, out of a ſenſual love to our ſelves, too prone to preſſe God with that requeſt of IABEZ; <hi>O that thou wouldſt bleſſe me indeed, and inlarge my coaſts, and that thy hand might be with mee, and that thou wouldſt keepe me from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, that it may not hurt me:</hi> ſo that God knowing bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter how to give, then wee know how to aske, as oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in his anger he gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth our requeſts, ſo oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times again in his love de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth them; <hi>&amp; male uſurus eo quod vult accipere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Iohan. Tract. <hi>73.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>deo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius miſerante non accipit,</hi> and ſuch things which hee foreſeeth wee aske to our
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:1344:123"/> owne hurt, he granteth us a favor in not granting them. When BALAAM tempted with the rewards of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation brought unto him by the Princes of <hi>Balack,</hi> was deſirous to goe and to curſe <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and for this cauſe ask't counſell of <hi>God;</hi> the firſt anſwere he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, is a <hi>Noli me tangere, Touch me not, doe not intreat me; for thou ſhalt not goe with them, Thou ſhalt not curſe this people, for they are bleſſed.</hi> But upon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond meſſage, when <hi>Balack</hi> ſendeth more Princes, and more honorable, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to promote him, and grant what ever he ſhould ask, he commeth the ſecond time to God, and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:1344:123"/> hee was ſo earneſt, <hi>Riſe up,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>and goe with them:</hi> but preſently we read that the anger of the Lord was kindled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, becauſe hee went; and wee finde him branded by St. <hi>Peter</hi> with the perpetuall ignominie of <hi>loving the wages of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe;</hi> for the love wherof we read afterward that even by the hand of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for whoſe ſlaughter he was ſo ready to bee hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, himſelf was ſlain.<note place="margin">Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b. 31.</note> Thus oft times upon the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous deſires of worldly bleſſings God puts men off by the directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his word by the motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of his ſpirit, with a <hi>Touch me not;</hi> do not for theſe things ſo earneſtly
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:1344:124"/> ſolicite me: for that which you hope will raiſe you, may chance to be your ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine. But yet if with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous affection the heart be ſo ſtrong fixt, that it wil not be removed, he giveth them their harts deſire, and according to the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their heart, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth them to inlarge their eſtate, and make their gaine their godlines: and now in a ſenſuall jollity, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are moſt curſt, are they forward moſt to bleſſe themſelves, with a <hi>Soule take thy caſe, for thou haſt now enough layd up in ſtore:</hi> when as wee know there is no evill more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon under the Sun, then goods thus purchaſed, to
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:1344:124"/> prove the undoing of the purchaſer, <hi>the ſtone will cry out of the wall, and the beame out of the timber will make anſwer; Woe to the man that thus addes houſe to houſe, and land to land.</hi> For what ſhal it profit thee for a time to have gain'd the whole world,<note place="margin">Salvian. ad Eccleſ. Cathol. l. <hi>3</hi>
               </note> &amp; in the end to looſe thine owne ſoule for ever? <hi>Et infaeliciſſime omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas quam bene alii poſt te vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, non cogitas quam male ipſe moriaris,</hi> and unhappy wretch thou art, to pleaſe thy ſelfe to think how hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily thy poſterity, rais'd by thy art and induſtry, ſhall live, and never once think'ſt how miſerably thy ſelfe muſt dye. And indeed ſtrange and wonderful it is
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:1344:125"/> to ſee the impotent deſire of the world, to purchaſe good houſe, good la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, good drink, good aire, &amp; yet how ſlender is their care to bee good themſelves;<note place="margin">Aug. Civ. Dei, lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quaſi hoc ſit homini maximum bonum, habere bona omnia praeter ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum,</hi> as if this were the chief good of man, to have all things good about him but himſelf.<note place="margin">Deut. 3.</note> As then wee read, that when <hi>Moſes</hi> made that paſſionate petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> unto God, <hi>O Lord thou haſt begun to ſhew thy ſervant thy great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and thy mighty hand; let me I pray thee go over, and ſee that good land beyond Iordan;</hi> God with a ſhort anſwer ſtops his mouth, <hi>let it ſuffice thee, ſpeak no more of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for thou ſhalt not goe:</hi> ſo
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:1344:125"/> if ſometime our earthly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires ſhall make the like pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions unto God, may we prevent his anſwer by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to our ſelves, <hi>Let it ſuffice thee</hi> to have ſpoke once or twice, and if he wil not heare thee, ſpeake no more. And indeed what madnes is it for a man to be importunatly ſolicitous for ſuch things, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not whether they will prove unto him good or il? For notwithſtanding that great licentiouſnes w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly wealth &amp; honor u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpe unto themſelves; ſo ſtrict an impoſition doe we finde layd upon all things under the Sunne, that hee that ſhall ſeriouſly bethink himſelf of his account, and
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:1344:126"/> that of him who receiveth much, much ſhall bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd; ſhal find perhaps the ods to be but very litle, not to have the world to uſe; or (as St. PAVL requires) <hi>to uſe the world, as if we us'd it not;</hi> unleſſe in truth the taske may prove more eaſie, with patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to want the world, then with moderation to injoy it. <hi>Quotus enim quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſapientum eſt cui non creſcat cum proſperitate vitioſitas?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Salvian de Guber. Dei, lib. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> For it is a great hazard to the vertue of a wiſe man, but that if riches increaſe, ſin wil increaſe too. <hi>Labour not then for the meat that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth,</hi> nor take much thought for the bleſſings of this life. For al theſe things touch not, trouble not the
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:1344:126"/> Maſter; with an honeſt and faire endeavor of our own dayly to aske our dayly bread it will ſuffice; if we wil importune him, let us make choyſe of bleſſings worth our importunity, &amp; not for religion onely, but for ſhame; leſt it ſhould bee ſaid that we are more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of our bodies then our ſoules, let us <hi>firſt ſeeke the Kingdome of God, and his righteouſneſſe,</hi> and then though in a low condition, it will be no hard matter to attaine unto that height of happines which St. <hi>Hierom</hi> commends in one of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout women; <hi>quae unius cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lula clauſa anguſtiis latitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne paradiſi frucbatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De laudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Aſellae. Ep. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.</hi>
               </note> though cloiſtered within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:1344:127"/> of a narrow Cell, by divine contemplation to expatiate throughout the whole latitude of Heaven. So ſhall we put more glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in our heart, then if our corne and wine were never ſo plentifully increaſt, and alwaies ſuch bleſſings God is beſt pleas'd to grant, which are moſt profitable for us to receive.</p>
            <p>Secondly wee may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that as <hi>Chriſt</hi> fruſtrats the expectation of <hi>Mary</hi> in denying the worldly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings ſhe deſireth: ſo, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her againe, he exceeds her expectation in propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the hope of heavenly bleſſings, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe now thought on No ſooner did <hi>Mary</hi> (rapt with a ſodaine
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:1344:127"/> joy) cry out <hi>Rabboni,</hi> have I found thee, O thou whom my ſoule loveth; no ſooner could ſhe fall downe and worſhip him, as for joy that he was riſen, ſo in hope that ſhe ſhould bee rais'd too, rais'd to honour in in that new Kingdome which ſhee perſwaded her ſelfe would now ſhortly be reſtored, but preſently all this conceited happines is blaſted, with a <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> Touch mee not. Doe not therefore honour me, as if I were now riſen to raiſe you to honour here on earth; for though I be riſen, I am not yet aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended, and till I be aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you muſt waite: yet with the ſame breath wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:1344:128"/> ſhee is diſheartned, ſhe is comforted again; for as the <hi>Yet</hi> in my text plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intimateth, and the end of the verſe expreſſeth it, he was ſhortly to aſcend <hi>to his Father, and their Father, to his God, and their God;</hi> &amp; then and there would hee build up the houſes, ſet up the thrones, and make them all Kings and Prieſts. Thus is it uſuall with GOD to with hold leſſer bleſſings, where hee intendeth to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow greater: for the earth, whereon MARY had now ſeated the throne of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, ſhall not be worthy to bee the footſtoole of that happines, which he inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to prepare. Indeed if in this life only wee had hope of
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:1344:128"/> all men, good men were moſt miſerable. But <hi>bleſſed be God</hi> (ſaith St. PAVL) <hi>who hath bleſſed us with all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall bleſsings, in coeleſtibus, in things heavenly, in places heavenly:</hi> and againe, <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God</hi> (ſaith St. PETER) <hi>who hath begotten us unto a lively hope, to an inheritance incorruptible, reſerved for us in the Heavens:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore oft times withdrawes his favors from us in the depth below, that wee may the more earneſtly ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the height above. For as God made ſome creatures meerly heavenly, without any dependance for their preſervation upon things below, others meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly earthly, without any
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:1344:129"/> hope or expectation of any happineſſe above: ſo hee made man in a condition betweene both, his body from the earth earthly, but his ſoule a ſparke fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; &amp; according to the two different parts whereof he doth conſiſt, he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided him two different manſions; firſt the earth, and then the Heaven. Now however betweene theſe two manſions there be no compare; for the earth, which we ſee, is temporall; but the Heaven which wee ſee not, is eternall: yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, as in the abſence of MOSES the people come flocking unto AARON, and <hi>Make thou Gods,</hi> ſay they, <hi>to goe before us, for as for this</hi>
               <pb n="253" facs="tcp:1344:129"/> MOSES <hi>we know not what is become of him:</hi> ſo in the abſence of Heaven wee are too prone to lay hold upon the earth, and ſet our affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon things below; the providence of God hath purpoſely blaſted the felicitie of all things ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunarie, ſet a <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> vanitie and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſpirit on them all, that even this vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here on earth, may raiſe our ſpirits up to Heaven, with a <hi>Domine illic tabernacula,</hi> Lord let us there, there make our Tabernacles. For a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las the earth it hath no conſtant forme nor come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and when we look upon it, there is no
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:1344:130"/> true beauty that we ſhould deſire it. If we complaine that long and tedious is our expectation here on earth, before ever we can come to injoy thoſe felicities in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, let us ſolace our ſelves to think, that it is enough, &amp; abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly enough, <hi>that the Diſciple be as his Maſter, and the ſervant as his Lord:</hi> now let us look upon our Lord and Maſter, and forty daies is he tempted in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, hungry, and thirſty in a barren and dry land, &amp; <hi>yet</hi> he is not aſcended. <hi>The Foxes have holes, the Birds of the aire have neſts, the Son of man not where to lay his head;</hi> and <hi>yet</hi> he is not aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. He is betrayed, arreig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, condemned, crucified,
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:1344:130"/> buried, and <hi>yet</hi> he is not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended. And that we may know this delay of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not out of any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency, but was meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and exemplarie unto us, he riſeth againe, and the ſame power of his, which rais'd him from the grave, could preſently have lifted him up to Heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth viſiting, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forting, inſtructing his Diſciples, &amp; <hi>yet</hi> he is not aſcended. The Lord himſelf, you ſee, hath tarried, tarried our leyſure, tarried for us, and ſhall not we waite patiently and tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the leyſure of the Lord. Perhaps he therfore makes us tarry, that daily here ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our grace, hee may one day adde alſo to our
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:1344:131"/> glory: <hi>Et libenter ſuſcipiam diſpenſationis moram magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine favoris duplicatam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. ep. <hi>33.</hi> ad Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratium.</note> and who would not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare the principal a while, to receive it hereafter with ſuch intereſt? perhaps ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore himſelf tarries, becauſe we are not yet prepared for his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming. We complaine oft times, upon the ſenſe of ſicknes, and ſorrow; <hi>How long Lord, how long wilt thou abſent thy ſelfe?</hi> Whenas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed upon the conſcience of our ſins, we might rather turn our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how long Lord, how lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g have we bin abſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee? Thy word hath been ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preacht unto us, <hi>in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, out of ſeaſon,</hi> by thy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters teaching, reproving,
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:1344:131"/> exhorting, and <hi>yet</hi> we have not obey'd. Thy grace hath bin graciouſly offred unto us, al the day long ſtanding at the dore of our harts and knocking, and <hi>yet</hi> we have not opened. Thou haſt made open proclamation; <hi>Come unto me all yee that are weary and heavy laden, and I will eaſe you:</hi> and <hi>yet</hi> though never ſo heavie laden, wee will not bee weary of our ſinnes, wee will not ſeeke out for eaſe. Can wee then wonder that God ſhould yet delay to put an end unto our ſorrowes, when as our ſelves have yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd to put an end unto our ſinnes? Can wee bee impatient at the forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of that happineſſe,
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:1344:132"/> which if God ſhould deale with us, as we with him, not yet, nor yet, nor ever, ſhould we bee ſo happy to enjoy? <hi>Why art thou then ſo troubled, O my ſoule;</hi> may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very pious ſoule now ſay, <hi>and why art thou ſo diſquieted within me? delight thou in the Lord, and hee will give thee thy hearts deſire.</hi> If thou faile of thy hearts deſire on earth (<hi>Mary</hi> her ſelf you ſee hath thus been diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) yet thou ſhalt abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bee recompenc't in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. For though here thou ſeem'ſt to be but dead, dead in regard of the fruition of any great felicity in this life, dead in the opinion of the meere natural man, who beleeveth not the hope of
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:1344:132"/> any life to come; yet thou haft a life hidden with Chriſt in God, and when Chriſt who is thy life ſhal appeare, then ſhalt thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo appeare with him in Glory.</p>
            <p>Laſtly as you have ſeene whether Chriſt is aſcended &amp; where he wil be <hi>Toucht,</hi> ſo now behold to whom he is aſcended, and what hopes we have to <hi>Touch</hi> him. My text tels you that as he was to aſcend ſo he aſcended to his Father. Now if you ſhall ſay that Chriſt had a Father to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to, and a <hi>Father pitieth his owne child;</hi> but how ſhal we aſcend, <hi>ſhew vs a Father too and it ſufficeth?</hi> I will ſhew you: and indeed with
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:1344:133"/> joy of heart we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that all the honours of Chriſt are for the moſt part diffuſive and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicative, and even of this neare Relation of Father &amp; Sonne we alſo doe partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate. <hi>Thou art my Sonne,</hi> my onely begotten Son, ſaith the Father vnto him, <hi>In whom I am well pleas'd;</hi> and pleaſ'd ſo well, that in him he hath reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cil'd the world vnto himſelfe, of enemies he hath made us his adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sons, and given us the priviledge to pray vnto him, <hi>Abba Father.</hi> If then my Text will not content you, read but the words following, and you can wiſh no more: <hi>Goe to my Brethren, and ſay vnto them,
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:1344:133"/> I aſcend vnto my Father;</hi> but he ſtayes not there, <hi>To my Father,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and your Father, to my God, and your God.</hi> And ſurely, as when the Father giveth the Son, ſo when the Son giveth the Father, <hi>together with him he will give us all things.</hi> And indeed when I compare both Teſtaments together, &amp; obſerve at ſundry times thoſe divers manners, whereby God in his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath pleaſ'd to make manifeſt, not the effects on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but even the language of his love; me thinks, (as after ſome cloudy ſtorme, I ſee the Heavens looke cleare, againe and ſmiling) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before God ſpake, as it were in a mighty winde &amp;
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:1344:134"/> Earthquake, looking high and holding his people un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with thoſe Majeſticke names of <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Hoſts;</hi> now with a courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous affabilitie he hath bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Heavens, ſpeaketh in a ſtill &amp; a ſoft voice, &amp; as if he had ſet a vaile before his Majeſtie, calleth himſelfe <hi>our Father,</hi> and <hi>the God of peace.</hi> And ſurely but this ſingle compellation <hi>Father</hi> proceeding from a piouſly devoted ſoule, attended with ſighes &amp; groanes, the Heares moſt powerfull O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorie, is able to make ſuch requeſts, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> as our ſelves oftimes, for feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, know not how to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſo neither doth God know how to deny. The
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:1344:134"/> Prodigall you ſee, after hee had ſpent all, &amp; that vngra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly too, yet when hee thinkes upon the gracious name of <hi>Father. I will goe to my Father,</hi> ſaith he, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but with a reſolution onely to ſay, <hi>Father I have ſinned,</hi> he is anticipated w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> imbracements, &amp; by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent wellcome hath his pardon ſeal'd unto him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he could have time to aske it. For the armes of Gods mercy, they are like the windore of <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke: if the Dove, our ſoule ſhal ſometime fly out, &amp; the overflowings of vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall make us afraid, let us returne upon the wing, &amp; with humility &amp; repentance crave a new ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:1344:135"/> and behold all the day long are theſe armes of his wide open to embrace us, and reſtore us to our reſt again. For <hi>doth a Father pity his owne child,</hi> and will not the Lord bee mercifull to them that feare him? nay <hi>call no man Father</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, for beyond all naturall affection we have a Father in Heaven, and his love is like that of <hi>Ionathan</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> even <hi>greater then the love of women.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> intercedeth for <hi>Sodom,</hi> you ſee hee puts in many doubts and feares, <hi>I have taken upon me to ſpeake, who am but duſt and aſhes; and let not my Lord be angry, and once more, and once more let me ſpeake:</hi> and ſtill hee
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:1344:135"/> feareth, and ſtill hee ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, and ſtill he obtaineth what he ſpeaketh for: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth God in mercy ceaſe to grant his petitions, till he in modeſty giveth them over. Thus ſometime if the conſcience of our ſinnes, and terrour of the throne of Iuſtice, and thoſe terrible names of <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>jealous God,</hi> ſhall make us to tremble, and be exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afraid, as indeed in this confident age it is good that we ſhould ſometime bee frighted, yet upon our true humiliation and contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we may boldly appeale from the throne of Iuſtice to the throne of Grace, and that gracious name of <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nough the
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:1344:136"/> fleſh have been a <hi>Sodome,</hi> yet if the ſpirit now become an <hi>Abraham,</hi> duſt and aſhes as we are, we may ſpeake; and once more, and once more may we ſpeake, til we bring our ſins, from fifty ſhall I ſay? nay from an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable number, for <hi>who knowes how oft he offends?</hi> to forty; to twenty, to tenne, to nothing; and blot them out of the booke of Gods remembrance. Let me then ſay once againe, <hi>Why art thou ſo diſquieted O my ſoule, and why art thou ſo troubled within me? put thou thy truſt in the Lord, and bee doing good,</hi> implore the adoption of a ſonne, and get thy ſoule ſeal'd unto the day of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and then with
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:1344:136"/> confidence maiſt thou ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before the Tribunall of God, where thou ſhalt finde the Iudge thy Father, thine Advocate thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>But let us beware that we doe not pleaſe and content our ſelves with a titular al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance, for it is not a <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> nor <hi>my Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Salvian ad Eccleſ. Cathol. l. <hi>3</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> will ſuffice. <hi>Aſſumptio religioſi nominis ſpon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votionis.</hi> Our challenging of God to bee our Father, chalengeth from us the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Sonnes. For as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, if they were obedient unto his will, and with care and conſcience did performe their ſervice to their Lord, he did ſhew himſelfe a <hi>Father</hi> to his
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:1344:137"/> 
               <hi>ſervants;</hi> ſo under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, if like graceleſſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren wee ſhall neglect the will of our heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he will ſhew himſelfe a <hi>Lord</hi> unto his <hi>Sonnes:</hi> and as then not every one that cryed <hi>Lord,</hi> ſo nor now e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that prayeth <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> but he that doth the will, whether of Lord or Father, he and he alone ſhal be acceptable in his ſight.</p>
            <p>So then to draw all to a concluſion. As wee are all already <hi>filii regni,</hi> children of the Kingdome, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to be Saints; ſo becauſe wee know ſuch children for their diſobedience may in the end bee ſhut out of this Kingdome, let us ſtrive to be <hi>filii regnantes,</hi> to reign
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:1344:137"/> as children in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and make our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſure. CHRIST is now aſcended up on high unto his Father, and hath given guifts to us, ſuch as will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able us to follow him; let us then bee carefull ſo to improve theſe guifts, to <hi>adde to our Faith vertue, to vertue knowledge,</hi> tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, patience, godlineſſe, and charity, that as our graces riſe, ſo may our hope of glory riſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and when age and death ſhall preſſe downe our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to the grave, our ſoules may be lifted up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and take a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable farewell of our friends, even in the very language of our Saviour;
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:1344:138"/> 
               <hi>Weepe not for mee, but for your ſelves, for I am now aſcending to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to my God, and your God. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>FOr <hi>Iohanni</hi> read <hi>Iohanne, pag</hi> 8. neceſsitude <hi>read</hi> viciſsitude, <hi>p.</hi> 11, ſo <hi>r.</hi> and, <hi>p.</hi> 25, laſt <hi>r.</hi> left, <hi>p.</hi> 46, that <hi>dele, p.</hi> 47, 1. <hi>dele, p.</hi> 53, for <hi>dele, p.</hi> 63, our <hi>r.</hi> one, <hi>p.</hi> 72, ſtrong <hi>r.</hi> ſtrange, <hi>p.</hi> 77. <hi>beneficii</hi> r. <hi>beneficiis, p.</hi> 111, <hi>partunebat</hi> r <hi>parturi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebat, p.</hi> 122, <hi>filiis</hi> r. <hi>filium, p.</hi> 143, ſuccentunate <hi>r.</hi> ſuccenturiate, <hi>p.</hi> 150, Thoſe <hi>r.</hi> theſe <hi>p</hi> 153, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, and <hi>r.</hi> and heavie, <hi>p.</hi> 177, Nor <hi>r.,</hi> nor, <hi>ibid.</hi> vvherever <hi>r.</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ever, <hi>p,</hi> 183, puniſheth <hi>r.</hi> pincheth, <hi>p,</hi> 203, this <hi>r,</hi> the, <hi>p,</hi> 208, an <hi>r,</hi> on, <hi>p,</hi> 212, <hi>cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divi</hi> r, <hi>cuſtodiri, p.</hi> 216, that thou <hi>r,</hi> that ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes thou, <hi>p,</hi> 223, hold <hi>r,</hi> hold, <hi>p,</hi> 225, have <hi>r,</hi> but have, <hi>p,</hi> 227, We <hi>r.,</hi> we. <hi>p,</hi> 32, <hi>dele</hi> 2. p, 256, <hi>favor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> r, <hi>foenoris, p,</hi> 258, nor <hi>r,</hi> nor.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1344:138"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
